Preface to Second Edition

The demand for a second edition of The Twenty Years’ Crisis faced the author with a difficult decision. A work on international politics completed in the summer of 1939, however rigorously it eschewed prophecy, necessarily bore marks of its time in substance, in phraseology, in its use of tenses and, above all, in such phrases as ‘the War’, ‘post-War’ and so forth, which can no longer be related without a strong effort on the part of the reader to the war of 1914–18. When, however, I approached the task of revision, it soon became clear that if I sought to rewrite every passage which had been in some way affected by the subsequent march of events, I should be producing not a second edition of an old book but essentially a new one; and this would have been a clumsy and unprofitable attempt to force new wine into old bottles. The Twenty Years’ Crisis remains a study of the period between the two wars written as that period was coming to an end and must be treated on its merits as such. What I have done, therefore, is to recast phrases which would be misleading or difficult to readers now far remote in time from the original context, to modify a few sentences which have invited misunderstanding, and to remove two or three passages relating to current controversies which have been eclipsed or put in a different perspective by the lapse of time.

On the other hand, I have changed nothing of substance, and have not sought to modify expressions of opinion merely on the ground that I should not unreservedly endorse them to-day. Perhaps, therefore, I may be permitted to indicate here the two main respects in which I am conscious of having since departed to some degree from the outlook reflected in these pages.

In the first place, The Twenty Years’ Crisis was written with the deliberate aim of counteracting the glaring and dangerous defect of nearly all thinking, both academic and popular, about international politics in English-speaking countries from 1919 to 1939 – the almost total neglect of the factor of power. To-day this defect, though it sometimes recurs when items of a future settlement are under discussion, has been to a considerable extent overcome; and some passages of The Twenty Years’ Crisis state their argument with a rather one-sided emphasis which no longer seems as necessary or appropriate to-day as it did in 1939.

Secondly, the main body of the book too readily and too complacently accepts the existing nation-state, large or small, as the unit of international society, though the final chapter offers some reflexions, to which subsequent events have added point, on the size of the political and economic units of the future. The conclusion now seems to impose itself on any unbiased observer that the small independent nation-state is obsolete or obsolescent and that no workable international organisation can be built on a membership of a multiplicity of nation-states. My present views on this point have been worked out in a small book recently published under the title Nationalism and After, and I can therefore with the better conscience take the only practicable course and leave the present work substantially as it was completed in 1939.

E. H. CARR

15 November 1945

Preface to First Edition

This book, which was originally planned in 1937, was sent to the press in the middle of July 1939 and had reached page proof when war broke out on 3 September 1939. To introduce into the text a few verbal modifications hastily made in the light of that event would have served little purpose; and I have accordingly preferred to leave it exactly as it was written at a time when war was already casting its shadow on the world, but when all hope of averting it was not yet lost. Wherever, therefore, such phrases as ‘the war’, ‘pre-war’ or ‘post-war’ occur in the following pages, the reader will understand that the reference is to the War of 1914–18.

When the passions of war are aroused, it becomes almost fatally easy to attribute the catastrophe solely to the ambitions and the arrogance of a small group of men, and to seek no further explanation. Yet even while war is raging, there may be some practical importance in an attempt to analyse the underlying and significant, rather than the immediate and personal, causes of the disaster. If and when peace returns to the world, the lessons of the breakdown which has involved Europe in a second major war within twenty years and two months of the Versailles Treaty will need to be earnestly pondered. A settlement which, having destroyed the National Socialist rulers of Germany, leaves untouched the conditions which made the phenomenon of National Socialism possible, will run the risk of being as short-lived and as tragic as the settlement of 1919. No period of history will better repay study by the peacemakers of the future than The Twenty Years’ Crisis which fills the interval between the two Great Wars. The next Peace Conference, if it is not to repeat the fiasco of the last, will have to concern itself with issues more fundamental than the drawing of frontiers. In this belief, I have ventured to dedicate this book to the makers of the coming peace.

The published sources from which I have derived help and inspiration are legion. I am specially indebted to two books which, though not specifically concerned with international relations, seem to me to have illuminated some of the fundamental problems of politics: Dr Karl Mannheim’s Ideology and Utopia and Dr Reinhold Niebuhr’s Moral Man and Immoral Society. Mr Peter Drucker’s The End of Economic Man, which did not come into my hands until my manuscript was virtually complete, contains some brilliant guesses and a most stimulating and suggestive diagnosis of the present crisis in world history. Many excellent historical and descriptive works about various aspects of international relations have appeared in the last twenty years, and my indebtedness to some of these is recorded in endnotes, which must take the place of a bibliography. But not one of these works known to me has attempted to analyse the profounder causes of the contemporary international crisis.

My obligations to individuals are still more extensive. In particular, I desire to record my deep gratitude to three friends who found time to read the whole of my manuscript, whose comments were equally stimulating whether they agreed or disagreed with my views, and whose suggestions are responsible for a great part of such value as this book possesses: Charles Manning, Professor of International Relations in the London School of Economics and Political Science; Dennis Routh, Fellow of All Souls College, Oxford, and recently Lecturer in International Politics in the University College of Wales, Aberystwyth; and a third, whose official position deprives me of the pleasure of naming him here. During the past three years I have been a member of a Study Group of the Royal Institute of International Affairs engaged on an enquiry into the problem of nationalism, the results of which are about to be published.1 The lines of investigation pursued by this Group have sometimes touched or crossed those which I have been following in these pages; and my colleagues in this Group and other contributors to its work have, in the course of our long discussions, unwittingly made numerous valuable contributions to the present book. To these, and to the many others who, in one way or another, consciously or unconsciously, have given me assistance and encouragement in the preparation of this volume, I tender my sincere thanks.

E. H. CARR

30 September 1939

1.

|   |

Nationalism: A study by a Group of Members of the Royal Institute of International Affairs (Oxford University Press).

CHAPTER ONE

The Beginning of a Science

The science of international politics is in its infancy. Down to 1914, the conduct of international relations was the concern of persons professionally engaged in it. In democratic countries, foreign policy was traditionally regarded as outside the scope of party politics; and the representative organs did not feel themselves competent to exercise any close control over the mysterious operations of foreign offices. In Great Britain, public opinion was readily aroused if war occurred in any region traditionally regarded as a sphere of British interest, or if the British navy momentarily ceased to possess that margin of superiority over potential rivals which was then deemed essential. In continental Europe, conscription and the chronic fear of foreign invasion had created a more general and continuous popular awareness of international problems. But this awareness found expression mainly in the labour movement, which from time to time passed somewhat academic resolutions against war. The constitution of the United States of America contained the unique provision that treaties were concluded by the President ‘by and with the advice and consent of the Senate’. But the foreign relations of the United States seemed too parochial to lend any wider significance to this exception. The more picturesque aspects of diplomacy had a certain news value. But nowhere, whether in universities or in wider intellectual circles, was there organized study of current international affairs. War was still regarded mainly as the business of soldiers; and the corollary of this was that international politics were the business of diplomats. There was no general desire to take the conduct of international affairs out of the hands of the professionals or even to pay serious and systematic attention to what they were doing.

The war of 1914–18 made an end of the view that war is a matter which affects only professional soldiers and, in so doing, dissipated the corresponding impression that international politics could safely be left in the hands of professional diplomats. The campaign for the popularization of international politics began in the English-speaking countries in the form of an agitation against secret treaties, which were attacked, on insufficient evidence, as one of the causes of the war. The blame for the secret treaties should have been imputed, not to the wickedness of the governments, but to the indifference of the peoples. Everybody knew that such treaties were concluded. But before the war of 1914 few people felt any curiosity about them or thought them objectionable.1 The agitation against them was, however, a fact of immense importance. It was the first symptom of the demand for the popularization of international politics and heralded the birth of a new science.

Purpose and analysis in political science

The science of international politics has, then, come into being in response to a popular demand. It has been created to serve a purpose and has, in this respect, followed the pattern of other sciences. At first sight, this pattern may appear illogical. Our first business, it will be said, is to collect, classify and analyse our facts and draw our inferences; and we shall then be ready to investigate the purpose to which our facts and our deductions can be put. The processes of the human mind do not, however, appear to develop in this logical order. The human mind works, so to speak, backwards. Purpose, which should logically follow analysis, is required to give it both its initial impulse and its direction. ‘If society has a technical need,’ wrote Engels, ‘it serves as a greater spur to the progress of science than do ten universities.’2 The first extant textbook of geometry ‘lays down an aggregate of practical rules designed to solve concrete problems: “rule for measuring a round fruitery”; “rule for laying out a field”; “computation of the fodder consumed by geese and oxen” ‘.3 Reason, says Kant, must approach nature ‘not . . . in the character of a pupil, who listens to all that his master chooses to tell him, but in that of a judge, who compels the witnesses to reply to those questions which he himself thinks fit to propose’.4 ‘We cannot study even stars or rocks or atoms’, writes a modern sociologist, ‘without being somehow determined, in our modes of systematization, in the prominence given to one or another part of our subject, in the form of the questions we ask and attempt to answer, by direct and human interests.’5 It is the purpose of promoting health which creates medical science, and the purpose of building bridges which creates the science of engineering. Desire to cure the sicknesses of the body politic has given its impulse and its inspiration to political science. Purpose, whether we are conscious of it or not, is a condition of thought; and thinking for thinking’s sake is as abnormal and barren as the miser’s accumulation of money for its own sake. ‘The wish is father to the thought’ is a perfectly exact description of the origin of normal human thinking.

If this is true of the physical sciences, it is true of political science in a far more intimate sense. In the physical sciences, the distinction between the investigation of facts and the purpose to which the facts are to be put is not only theoretically valid, but is constantly observed in practice. The laboratory worker engaged in investigating the causes of cancer may have been originally inspired by the purpose of eradicating the disease. But this purpose is in the strictest sense irrelevant to the investigation and separable from it. His conclusion can be nothing more than a true report on facts. It cannot help to make the facts other than they are; for the facts exist independently of what anyone thinks about them. In the political sciences, which are concerned with human behaviour, there are no such facts. The investigator is inspired by the desire to cure some ill of the body politic. Among the causes of the trouble, he diagnoses the fact that human beings normally react to certain conditions in a certain way. But this is not a fact comparable with the fact that human bodies react in a certain way to certain drugs. It is a fact which may be changed by the desire to change it; and this desire, already present in the mind of the investigator, may be extended, as the result of his investigation, to a sufficient number of other human beings to make it effective. The purpose is not, as in the physical sciences, irrelevant to the investigation and separable from it: it is itself one of the facts. In theory, the distinction may no doubt still be drawn between the role of the investigator who establishes the facts and the role of the practitioner who considers the right course of action. In practice, one role shades imperceptibly into the other. Purpose and analysis become part and parcel of a single process.

A few examples will illustrate this point. Marx, when he wrote Capital, was inspired by the purpose of destroying the capitalist system just as the investigator of the causes of cancer is inspired by the purpose of eradicating cancer. But the facts about capitalism are not, like the facts about cancer, independent of the attitude of people towards it. Marx’s analysis was intended to alter, and did in fact alter, that attitude. In the process of analysing the facts, Marx altered them. To attempt to distinguish between Marx the scientist and Marx the propagandist is idle hair-splitting. The financial experts, who in the summer of 1932 advised the British Government that it was possible to convert 5 per cent War Loan at the rate of 3½ per cent, no doubt based their advice on an analysis of certain facts; but the fact that they gave this advice was one of the facts which, being known to the financial world, made the operation successful. Analysis and purpose were inextricably blended. Nor is it only the thinking of professional or qualified students of politics which constitutes a political fact. Everyone who reads the political columns of a newspaper or attends a political meeting or discusses politics with his neighbour is to that extent a student of politics; and the judgement which he forms becomes (especially, but not exclusively, in democratic countries) a factor in the course of political events. Thus a reviewer might conceivably criticize this book on the ground, not that it was false, but that it was inopportune; and this criticism, whether justified or not, would be intelligible, whereas the same criticism of a book about the causes of cancer would be meaningless. Every political judgement helps to modify the facts on which it is passed. Political thought is itself a form of political action. Political science is the science not only of what is, but of what ought to be.

The role of utopianism

If therefore purpose precedes and conditions thought, it is not surprising to find that, when the human mind begins to exercise itself in some fresh field, an initial stage occurs in which the element of wish or purpose is overwhelmingly strong, and the inclination to analyse facts and means weak or non-existent. Hobhouse notes as a characteristic of ‘the most primitive peoples’ that ‘the evidence of the truth of an idea is not yet separate from the quality which renders it pleasant’.6 The same would appear to be conspicuously true of the primitive, or ‘utopian’, stage of the political sciences. During this stage, the investigators will pay little attention to existing ‘facts’ or to the analysis of cause and effect, but will devote themselves wholeheartedly to the elaboration of visionary projects for the attainment of the ends which they have in view – projects whose simplicity and perfection give them an easy and universal appeal. It is only when these projects break down, and wish or purpose is shown to be incapable by itself of achieving the desired end, that the investigators will reluctantly call in the aid of analysis, and the study, emerging from its infantile and utopian period, will establish its claim to be regarded as a science. ‘Sociology’, remarks Professor Ginsberg, ‘may be said to have arisen by way of reaction against sweeping generalizations unsupported by detailed inductive enquiry.’7

It may not be fanciful to find an illustration of this rule even in the domain of physical science. During the Middle Ages, gold was a recognized medium of exchange. But economic relations were not sufficiently developed to require more than a limited amount of such a medium. When the new economic conditions of the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries introduced a widespread system of money transactions, and the supply of gold was found to be inadequate for the purpose, the wise men of the day began to experiment in the possibility of transmuting commoner metals into gold. The thought of the alchemist was purely purposive. He did not stop to enquire whether the properties of lead were such as to make it transmutable into gold. He assumed that the end was absolute (i.e. that gold must be produced), and that means and material must somehow be adapted to it. It was only when this visionary project ended in failure that the investigators were prompted to apply their thought to an examination of ‘facts’, i.e. the nature of matter; and though the initial utopian purpose of making gold out of lead is probably as far as ever from fulfilment, modern physical science has been evolved out of this primitive aspiration.

Other illustrations may be taken from fields more closely akin to our present subject.

It was in the fifth and fourth centuries BC that the first serious recorded attempts were made to create a science of politics. These attempts were made independently in China and in Greece. But neither Confucius nor Plato, though they were of course profoundly influenced by the political institutions under which they lived, really tried to analyse the nature of those institutions or to seek the underlying causes of the evils which they deplored. Like the alchemists, they were content to advocate highly imaginative solutions whose relation to existing facts was one of flat negation.8 The new political order which they propounded was as different from anything they saw around them as gold from lead. It was the product not of analysis, but of aspiration.

In the eighteenth century, trade in Western Europe had become so important as to render irksome the innumerable restrictions placed on it by governmental authority and justified by mercantilist theory. The protest against these restrictions took the form of a wishful vision of universal free trade; and out of this vision the physiocrats in France, and Adam Smith in Great Britain, created a science of political economy. The new science was based primarily on a negation of existing reality and on certain artificial and unverified generalizations about the behaviour of a hypothetical economic man. In practice, it achieved some highly useful and important results. But economic theory long retained its utopian character; and even to-day some ‘classical economists’ insist on regarding universal free trade – an imaginary condition which has never existed – as the normal postulate of economic science, and all reality as a deviation from this utopian prototype.9

In the opening years of the nineteenth century, the industrial revolution created a new social problem to engage human thought in Western Europe. The pioneers who first set out to tackle this problem were the men on whom posterity has bestowed the name of ‘utopian socialists’: Saint-Simon and Fourier in France, Robert Owen in England. These men did not attempt to analyse the nature of class-interests or class-consciousness or of the class-conflict to which they gave rise. They simply made unverified assumptions about human behaviour and, on the strength of these, drew up visionary schemes of ideal communities in which men of all classes would live together in amity, sharing the fruits of their labours in proportion to their needs. For all of them, as Engels remarked, ‘socialism is the expression of absolute truth, reason and justice, and needs only be discovered in order to conquer all the world in virtue of its own power’.10 The utopian socialists did valuable work in making men conscious of the problem and of the need of tackling it. But the solution propounded by them had no logical connexion with the conditions which created the problem. Once more, it was the product not of analysis, but of aspiration.

Schemes elaborated in this spirit would not, of course, work. Just as nobody has ever been able to make gold in a laboratory, so nobody has ever been able to live in Plato’s republic or in a world of universal free trade or in Fourier’s phalansteries. But it is, nevertheless, perfectly right to venerate Confucius and Plato as the founders of political science, Adam Smith as the founder of political economy, and Fourier and Owen as the founders of socialism. The initial stage of aspiration towards an end is an essential foundation of human thinking. The wish is father to the thought. Teleology precedes analysis.

The teleological aspect of the science of international politics has been conspicuous from the outset. It took its rise from a great and disastrous war; and the overwhelming purpose which dominated and inspired the pioneers of the new science was to obviate a recurrence of this disease of the international body politic. The passionate desire to prevent war determined the whole initial course and direction of the study. Like other infant sciences, the science of international politics has been markedly and frankly utopian. It has been in the initial stage in which wishing prevails over thinking, generalization over observation, and in which little attempt is made at a critical analysis of existing facts or available means. In this stage, attention is concentrated almost exclusively on the end to be achieved. The end has seemed so important that analytical criticism of the means proposed has too often been branded as destructive and unhelpful. When President Wilson, on his way to the Peace Conference, was asked by some of his advisers whether he thought his plan of a League of Nations would work, he replied briefly: ‘If it won’t work, it must be made to work.’11 The advocate of a scheme for an international police force or for ‘collective security’, or of some other project for an international order, generally replied to the critic not by an argument designed to show how and why he thought his plan will work, but either by a statement that it must be made to work because the consequences of its failure to work would be so disastrous, or by a demand for some alternative nostrum.12 This must be the spirit in which the alchemist or the utopian socialist would have answered the sceptic who questioned whether lead could be turned into gold or men made to live in model communities. Thought has been at a discount. Much that was said and written about international politics between 1919 and 1939 merited the stricture applied in another context by the economist Marshall, who compares ‘the nervous irresponsibility which conceives hasty utopian schemes’ to the ‘bold facility of the weak player who will speedily solve the most difficult chess problem by taking on himself to move the black men as well as the white’.13 In extenuation of this intellectual failure, it may be said that, during the earlier of these years, the black pieces in international politics were in the hands of such weak players that the real difficulties of the game were scarcely manifest even to the keenest intelligence. The course of events after 1931 clearly revealed the inadequacy of pure aspiration as the basis for a science of international politics, and made it possible for the first time to embark on serious critical and analytical thought about international problems.

The impact of realism

No science deserves the name until it has acquired sufficient humility not to consider itself omnipotent, and to distinguish the analysis of what is from aspiration about what should be. Because in the political sciences this distinction can never be absolute, some people prefer to withhold from them the right to the title of science. In both physical and political sciences, the point is soon reached where the initial stage of wishing must be succeeded by a stage of hard and ruthless analysis. The difference is that political sciences can never wholly emancipate themselves from utopianism, and that the political scientist is apt to linger for a longer initial period than the physical scientist in the utopian stage of development. This is perfectly natural. For while the transmutation of lead into gold would be no nearer if everyone in the world passionately desired it, it is undeniable that if everyone really desired a ‘world-state’ or ‘collective security’ (and meant the same thing by those terms), it would be easily attained; and the student of international politics may be forgiven if he begins by supposing that his task is to make everyone desire it. It takes him some time to understand that no progress is likely to be made along this path, and that no political utopia will achieve even the most limited success unless it grows out of political reality. Having made the discovery, he will embark on that hard ruthless analysis of reality which is the hallmark of science; and one of the facts whose causes he will have to analyse is the fact that few people do desire a ‘world-state’ or ‘collective security’, and that those who think they desire it mean different and incompatible things by it. He will have reached a stage when purpose by itself is seen to be barren, and when analysis of reality has forced itself upon him as an essential ingredient of his study.

The impact of thinking upon wishing which, in the development of a science, follows the breakdown of its first visionary projects, and marks the end of its specifically utopian period, is commonly called realism. Representing a reaction against the wish-dreams of the initial stage, realism is liable to assume a critical and somewhat cynical aspect. In the field of thought, it places its emphasis on the acceptance of facts and on the analysis of their causes and consequences. It tends to depreciate the role of purpose and to maintain, explicitly or implicitly, that the function of thinking is to study a sequence of events which it is powerless to influence or to alter. In the field of action, realism tends to emphasize the irresistible strength of existing forces and the inevitable character of existing tendencies, and to insist that the highest wisdom lies in accepting, and adapting oneself to, these forces and these tendencies. Such an attitude, though advocated in the name of ‘objective’ thought, may no doubt be carried to a point where it results in the sterilization of thought and the negation of action. But there is a stage where realism is the necessary corrective to the exuberance of utopianism, just as in other periods utopianism must be invoked to counteract the barrenness of realism. Immature thought is predominantly purposive and utopian. Thought which rejects purpose altogether is the thought of old age. Mature thought combines purpose with observation and analysis. Utopia and reality are thus the two facets of political science. Sound political thought and sound political life will be found only where both have their place.

Notes

1.

|   |

A recent historian of the Franco-Russian alliance, having recorded the protests of a few French radicals against the secrecy which enveloped this transaction, continues: ‘Parliament and opinion tolerated this complete silence, and were content to remain in absolute ignorance of the provisions and scope of the agreement’ (Michon, L’ Alliance Franco-Russe, p. 75). In 1898, in the Chamber of Deputies, Hanotaux was applauded for describing the disclosure of its terms as ‘absolutely impossible’ (ibid., p. 82).

2.

|   |

Quoted in Sidney Hook, Towards the Understanding of Karl Marx, p. 279.

3.

|   |

J. Rueff, From the Physical to the Social Sciences (Engl. transl.), p. 27.

4.

|   |

Kant, Critique of Pure Reason (Everyman ed.), p. 11.

5.

|   |

MacIver, Community, p. 56.

6.

|   |

L. T. Hobhouse, Development and Purpose, p. 100.

7.

|   |

M. Ginsberg, Sociology, p. 25.

8.

|   |

‘Plato and Plotinus, More and Campanella constructed their fanciful societies with those materials which were omitted from the fabric of the actual communities by the defects of which they were inspired. The Republic, the Utopia, and the City of the Sun were protests against a state of things which the experience of their authors taught them to condemn’ (Acton, History of Freedom, p. 270).

9.

|   |

‘L’économie politique libérale a été un des meilleurs exemples d’utopies qu’on puisse citer. On avait imagine’ une société où tout serait ramené à des types commerciaux, sous la loi de la plus compléte concurrence; on reconna1t aujourd’hui que cette société idéale serait aussi difficile à realiser que celle de Platon’ (Sorel, Refléxions sur la violence, p. 47). Compare Professor Robbins’ well-known defence of laissez-faire economics: ‘The idea of a co-ordination of human activity by means of a system of impersonal rules, within which what spontaneous relations arise are conducive to mutual benefit, is a conception at least as subtle, at least as ambitious, as the conception of prescribing each action or each type of action by a central planning authority; and it is perhaps not less in harmony with the requirements of a spiritually sound society’ (Economic Planning and International Order, p. 229). It would be equally true, and perhaps equally useful, to say that the constitution of Plato’s Republic is at least as subtle, ambitious and satisfying to spiritual requirements as that of any state which has ever existed.

10.

|   |

Engels, Socialism, Utopian and Scientific (Engl. transl.), p. 26.

11.

|   |

R. S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson and World Settlement, i. p. 93.

12.

|   |

‘There is the old well-known story about the man who, during the Lisbon earthquake of 1775, went about hawking anti-earthquake pills; but one incident is forgotten – when someone pointed out that the pills could not possibly be of use, the hawker replied: ‘But what would you put in their place?” ’ (L. B. Namier, In the Margin of History, p. 20).

13.

|   |

Economic Journal (1907), xvii. p. 9.

CHAPTER THREE

The Utopian Background

The foundations of utopianism

The modern school of utopian political thought must be traced back to the break-up of the mediaeval system, which presupposed a universal ethic and a universal political system based on divine authority. The realists of the Renaissance made the first determined onslaught on the primacy of ethics and propounded a view of politics which made ethics an instrument of politics, the authority of the state being thus substituted for the authority of the church as the arbiter of morality. The answer of the utopian school to this challenge was not an easy one. An ethical standard was required which would be independent of any external authority, ecclesiastical or civil; and the solution was found in the doctrine of a secular ‘law of nature’ whose ultimate source was the individual human reason. Natural law, as first propounded by the Greeks, had been an intuition of the human heart about what is morally right. ‘It is eternal’, said Sophocles’ Antigone, ‘and no man knows whence it came.’ The Stoics and the mediaeval schoolmen identified natural law with reason; and in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries this identification was revived in a new and special form. In science, the laws of nature were deduced by a process of reasoning from observed facts about the nature of matter. By an easy analogy, the Newtonian principles were now applied to the ethical problems. The moral law of nature could be scientifically established; and rational deduction from the supposed facts of human nature took the place of revelation or intuition as the source of morality. Reason could determine what were the universally valid moral laws; and the assumption was made that, once these laws were determined, human beings would conform to them just as matter conformed to the physical laws of nature. Enlightenment was the royal road to the millennium.

By the eighteenth century, the main lines of modern utopian thought were firmly established. It was essentially individualist in that it made the human conscience the final court of appeal in moral questions; in France it became associated with a secular, in England with an evangelical tradition. It was essentially rationalist in that it identified the human conscience with the voice of reason.1 But it had still to undergo important developments; and it was Jeremy Bentham who, when the industrial revolution had transferred the leadership of thought from France to England, gave to nineteenth-century utopianism its characteristic shape. Starting from the postulate that the fundamental characteristic of human nature is to seek pleasure and avoid pain, Bentham deduced from this postulate a rational ethic which defined the good in the famous formula ‘the greatest happiness of the greatest number’. As has often been pointed out, ‘the greatest happiness of the greatest number’ performed the function, which natural law had performed for a previous generation, of an absolute ethical standard. Bentham firmly believed in this absolute standard, and rejected as ‘anarchical’ the view that there are ‘as many standards of right and wrong as there are men’.2 In effect, ‘the greatest happiness of the greatest number’ was the nineteenth-century definition of the content of natural law.

The importance of Bentham’s contribution was twofold. In the first place, by identifying the good with happiness, he provided a plausible confirmation of the ‘scientific’ assumption of the eighteenth-century rationalists that man would infallibly conform to the moral law of nature once its content had been rationally determined. Secondly, while preserving the rationalist and individualist aspect of the doctrine, he succeeded in giving it a broader basis. The doctrine of reason in its eighteenth-century guise was pre-eminently intellectual and aristocratic. Its political corollary was an enlightened despotism of philosophers, who alone could be expected to have the necessary reasoning power to discover the good. But now that happiness was the criterion, the one thing needful was that the individual should understand where his happiness lay. Not only was the good ascertainable – as the eighteenth century had held – by a rational process, but this process – added the nineteenth century – was not a matter of abstruse philosophical speculation, but of simple common sense. Bentham was the first thinker to elaborate the doctrine of salvation by public opinion. The members of the community ‘may, in their aggregate capacity, be considered as constituting a sort of judicatory or tribunal – call it…The Public-Opinion Tribunal’.3 It was James Mill, Bentham’s pupil, who produced the most complete argument yet framed for the infallibility of public opinion:

Every man possessed of reason is accustomed to weigh evidence and to be guided and determined by its preponderance. When various conclusions are, with their evidence, presented with equal care and with equal skill, there is a moral certainty, though some few may be misguided, that the greatest number will judge right, and that the greatest force of evidence, whatever it is, will produce the greatest impression.4

This is not the only argument by which democracy as a political institution can be defended. But this argument was, in fact, explicitly or implicitly accepted by most nineteenth-century liberals. The belief that public opinion can be relied on to judge rightly on any question rationally presented to it, combined with the assumption that it will act in accordance with this right judgement, is an essential foundation of the liberal creed. In Great Britain, the later eighteenth and the nineteenth centuries were pre-eminently the age of popular preaching and of political oratory. By the voice of reason men could be persuaded both to save their own immortal souls and to move along the path of political enlightenment and progress. The optimism of the nineteenth century was based on the triple conviction that the pursuit of the good was a matter of right reasoning, that the spread of knowledge would soon make it possible for everyone to reason rightly on this important subject, and that anyone who reasoned rightly on it would necessarily act rightly.

The application of these principles to international affairs followed, in the main, the same pattern. The Abbe’ Saint-Pierre, who propounded one of the earliest schemes for a League of Nations, ‘was so confident in the reasonableness of his projects that he always believed that, if they were fairly considered, the ruling powers could not fail to adopt them’.5 Both Rousseau and Kant argued that, since wars were waged by princes in their own interest and not in that of their peoples, there would be no wars under a republican form of government. In this sense, they anticipated the view that public opinion, if allowed to make itself effective, would suffice to prevent war. In the nineteenth century, this view won widespread approval in Western Europe, and took on the specifically rationalist colour proper to the doctrine that the holding of the right moral beliefs and the performance of the right actions can be assured by process of reasoning. Never was there an age which so unreservedly proclaimed the supremacy of the intellect. ‘It is intellectual evolution’, averred Comte, ‘which essentially determines the main course of social phenomena.’6 Buckle, whose famous History of Civilisation was published between 1857 and 1861, boldly declared that dislike of war is ‘a cultivated taste peculiar to an intellectual people’. He chose a cogent example, based on the assumption, natural to a British thinker, of the ingrained bellicosity of Great Britain’s most recent enemy. ‘Russia is a warlike country’, he wrote, ‘not because the inhabitants are immoral, but because they are unintellectual. The fault is in the head, not in the heart.’7 The view that the spread of education would lead to international peace was shared by many of Buckle’s contemporaries and successors. Its last serious exponent was Sir Norman Angell, who sought, by The Great Illusion and other books, to convince the world that war never brought profit to anyone. If he could establish this point by irrefutable argument, thought Sir Norman, then war could not occur. War was simply a ‘failure of understanding’. Once the head was purged of the illusion that war was profitable, the heart could look after itself. ‘The world of the Crusades and of heretic burning’, ran the opening manifesto of a monthly journal called War and Peace which started publication in October 1913, ‘… was not a badly-meaning, but a badly-thinking world…We emerged from it by correcting a defect in understanding; we shall emerge from the world of political warfare or armed peace in the same way.’8 Reason could demonstrate the absurdity of the international anarchy; and with increasing knowledge, enough people would be rationally convinced of its absurdity to put an end to it.

Benthamism transplanted

Before the end of the nineteenth century, serious doubts had been thrown from more than one quarter on the assumptions of Benthamite rationalism. The belief in the sufficiency of reason to promote right conduct was challenged by psychologists. The identification of virtue with enlightened self-interest began to shock philosophers. The belief in the infallibility of public opinion had been attractive on the hypothesis of the earlier utilitarians that public opinion was the opinion of educated and enlightened men. It was less attractive, at any rate to those who thought themselves educated and enlightened, now that public opinion was the opinion of the masses; and as early as 1859, in his essay On Liberty, J. S. Mill had been preoccupied with the dangers of ‘the tyranny of the majority’. After 1900, it would have been difficult to find, either in Great Britain or in any other European country, any serious political thinker who accepted the Benthamite assumptions without qualification. Yet, by one of the ironies of history, these half-discarded nineteenth-century assumptions reappeared, in the second and third decades of the twentieth century, in the special field of international politics, and there became the foundation-stones of a new utopian edifice. The explanation may be in part that, after 1914, men’s minds naturally fumbled their way back, in search of a new utopia, to those apparently firm foundations of nineteenth-century peace and security. But a more decisive factor was the influence of the United States, still in the heyday of Victorian prosperity and of Victorian belief in the comfortable Benthamite creed. Just as Bentham, a century earlier, had taken the eighteenth-century doctrine of reason and refashioned it to the needs of the coming age, so now Woodrow Wilson, the impassioned admirer of Bright and Gladstone, transplanted the nineteenth-century rationalist faith to the almost virgin soil of international politics and, bringing it back with him to Europe, gave it a new lease of life. Nearly all popular theories of international politics between the two world wars were reflexions, seen in an American mirror, of nineteenth-century liberal thought.

In a limited number of countries, nineteenth-century liberal democracy had been a brilliant success. It was a success because its presuppositions coincided with the stage of development reached by the countries concerned. Out of the mass of current speculation, the leading spirits of the age took precisely that body of theory which corresponded to their needs, consciously and unconsciously fitting their practice to it, and it to their practice. Utilitarianism and laissez-faire served, and in turn directed, the course of industrial and commercial expansion. But the view that nineteenth-century liberal democracy was based, not on a balance of forces peculiar to the economic development of the period and the countries concerned, but on certain a priori rational principles which had only to be applied in other contexts to produce similar results, was essentially utopian; and it was this view which, under Wilson’s inspiration, dominated the world after the first world war. When the theories of liberal democracy were transplanted, by a purely intellectual process, to a period and to countries whose stage of development and whose practical needs were utterly different from those of Western Europe in the nineteenth century, sterility and disillusionment were the inevitable sequel. Rationalism can create a utopia, but cannot make it real. The liberal democracies scattered throughout the world by the peace settlement of 1919 were the product of abstract theory, stuck no roots in the soil, and quickly shrivelled away.

Rationalism and the League of Nations

The most important of all the institutions affected by this one-sided intellectualism of international politics was the League of Nations, which was an attempt ‘to apply the principles of Lockeian liberalism to the building of a machinery of international order’.9 ‘The Covenant’, observed General Smuts, ‘… simply carries into world affairs that outlook of a liberal democratic society which is one of the great achievements of our human advance.’10 But this transplantation of democratic rationalism from the national to the international sphere was full of unforeseen difficulties. The empiricist treats the concrete case on its individual merits. The rationalist refers it to an abstract general principle. Any social order implies a large measure of standardization, and therefore of abstraction; there cannot be a different rule for every member of the community. Such standardization is comparatively easy in a community of several million anonymous individuals conforming more or less closely to recognized types. But it presents infinite complications when applied to sixty known states differing widely in size, in power, and in political, economic and cultural development. The League of Nations, being the first large-scale attempt to standardize international political problems on a rational basis, was particularly liable to these embarrassments.

The founders of the League, some of whom were men of political experience and political understanding, had indeed recognized the dangers of abstract perfection. ‘Acceptance of the political facts of the present’, remarked the official British Commentary on the Covenant issued in 1919, ‘has been one of the principles on which the Commission has worked’,11 and this attempt to take account of political realities distinguished the Covenant not only from previous paper schemes of world organization, but also from such purely utopian projects as the International Police Force, the Kellogg-Briand Pact and the United States of Europe. The Covenant possessed the virtue of several theoretical imperfections. Purporting to treat all members as equal, it assured to the Great Powers a permanent majority on the Council of the League.12 It did not purport to prohibit war altogether, but only to limit the occasions on which it might legitimately be resorted to. The obligation imposed on members of the League to apply sanctions to the Covenant-breaker was not free from vagueness; and this vagueness had been discreetly enhanced by a set of ‘interpretative’ resolutions passed by the Assembly of 1921. The starkness of the territorial guarantee provided by Article 10 of the Covenant was smoothed away in a resolution which secured an almost unanimous vote at the Assembly of 1923. It seemed for the moment as if the League might reach a working compromise between utopia and reality and become an effective instrument of international politics.

Unhappily, the most influential European politicians neglected the League during its critical formative years. Abstract rationalism gained the upper hand, and from about 1922 onwards the current at Geneva set strongly in the utopian direction.13 It came to be believed, in the words of an acute critic, ‘that there can exist, either at Geneva or in foreign offices, a sort of carefully classified card-index of events or, better still, “situations”, and that, when the event happens or the situation presents itself, a member of the Council or Foreign Minister can easily recognize that event or situation and turn up the index to be directed to the files where the appropriate action is prescribed’.14 There were determined efforts to perfect the machinery, to standardize the procedure, to close the ‘gaps’ in the Covenant by an absolute veto on all war, and to make the application of sanctions ‘automatic’. The Draft Treaty of Mutual Assistance, the Geneva Protocol, the General Act, the plan to incorporate the Kellogg-Briand Pact in the Covenant and ‘the definition of the aggressor’, were all milestones on the dangerous path of rationalization. The fact that the utopian dishes prepared during these years at Geneva proved unpalatable to most of the principal governments concerned was a symptom of the growing divorce between theory and practice.

Even the language current in League circles betrayed the growing eagerness to avoid the concrete in favour of the abstract generalizations. When it was desired to arrange that the Draft Treaty of Mutual Assistance could be brought into force in Europe without waiting for the rest of the world, a stipulation was inserted that it might come into force ‘by continents’ – a proviso with farcical implications for every continent except Europe. A conventional phraseology came into use, which served as the current coin of delegates at Geneva and of League enthusiasts elsewhere and which, through constant repetition, soon lost all contact with reality. ‘I cannot recall any time,’ said Mr Churchill in 1932, ‘when the gap between the kind of words which statesmen used and what was actually happening in many countries was so great as it is now.’15 The Franco-Soviet Pact, which was a defensive alliance against Germany, was so drafted as to make it appear an instrument of general application, and was described as a shining example of the principle of ‘collective security’. A member of the House of Commons, when asked in the debate on sanctions in June 1936 whether he would run the risk of war with Italy, replied that he was prepared to face ‘all the consequences naturally flowing from the enforcement of the Covenant against an aggressor nation’.16 These linguistic contortions encouraged the frequent failure to distinguish between the world of abstract reason and the world of political reality. ‘Metaphysicians, like savages,’ remarks Mr Bertrand Russell, ‘are apt to imagine a magical connexion between words and things’.17 The metaphysicians of Geneva found it difficult to believe that an accumulation of ingenious texts prohibiting war was not a barrier against war itself. ‘Our purpose’, said M. Benes in introducing the Geneva Protocol to the 1924 Assembly, ‘was to make war impossible, to kill it, to annihilate it. To do this we had to create a system.’18 The Protocol was the ‘system’. Such presumption could only provoke nemesis. Once it came to be believed in League circles that salvation could be found in a perfect card-index, and that the unruly flow of international politics could be canalized into a set of logically impregnable abstract formulae inspired by the doctrines of nineteenth-century liberal democracy, the end of the League as an effective political instrument was in sight.

The apotheosis of public opinion

Nor did any better fortune attend the attempt to transplant to the international sphere the liberal democratic faith in public opinion. And here there was a double fallacy. The nineteenth-century belief in public opinion comprised two articles: first (and in democracies this was, with some reservations, true), that public opinion is bound in the long run to prevail; and second (this was the Benthamite view), that public opinion is always right. Both these beliefs, not always clearly distinguished one from the other, were uncritically reproduced in the sphere of international politics.

The first attempts to invoke public opinion as a force in the international world had been made in the United States. In 1909, President Taft evolved a plan for the conclusion of treaties between the United States and other Great Powers for the compulsory arbitration of international disputes. But how, it was asked, would the award of the arbitral court be enforced? Taft disposed of the question with complete light-heartedness. He had never observed that in a democracy like the United States the enforcement of awards gave rise to any particular difficulty; and he professed himself ‘very little concerned’ about this aspect of the matter. ‘After we have gotten the cases into court and decided, and the judgments embodied in a solemn declaration of a court thus established, few nations will care to face the condemnation of international public opinion and disobey the judgment.’19 Public opinion, as in democratic countries, was bound to prevail; and public opinion, as the Benthamites said, could always be trusted to come down on the right side. The United States Senate rejected the President’s proposal, so that the opportunity did not occur to put ‘international public opinion’ to the test. Four years later, Bryan, Wilson’s first Secretary of State, came forward with a further set of treaties. In the Bryan treaties, arbitration was dropped in favour of conciliation. Their most novel and significant feature was the provision that the parties to them should not resort to war until twelve months had elapsed from the beginning of the dispute. In hot blood, the Bryan treaties seemed to admit, men might not listen to the voice of reason. But once delay had cooled their passions, reason, in the guise of international public opinion, would resume her compelling force. Several such treaties were in fact signed between the United States and other Powers – some of them, by a curious irony, in the first days of the first world war. ‘The sum and substance’ of these treaties, said Wilson in October 1914, was ‘that whenever any trouble arises the light shall shine on it for a year before anything is done; and my prediction is that after the light has shone on it for a year, it will not be necessary to do anything; that after we know what happened, then we will know who was right and who was wrong.’20

The belief in the compelling power of reason, expressed through the voice of the people, was particularly congenial to Wilson. When he entered politics in 1910 as a candidate for the Governorship of New Jersey, his campaign was based on an appeal to ‘the people’ against the political bosses; and he displayed ‘an almost mystical faith that the people would follow him if he could speak to enough of them’. The result of his campaign confirmed him in his belief in the potency of the voice of reason speaking through his lips. He would govern by the persuasiveness of reason acting on an all-powerful public opinion. ‘If the bosses held back, he had only to appeal to the people.…The people wanted the high things, the right things, the true things.’21

America’s entry into the war entailed no modification of Wilson’s faith in the rightness of popular judgement. He took up the cue in one of the speeches in which he discussed the future conditions of peace:

It is the peculiarity of this great war that, while statesmen have seemed to cast about for definitions of their purpose and have sometimes seemed to shift their ground and their point of view, the thought of the mass of men, whom statesmen are supposed to instruct and lead, has grown more and more unclouded, more and more certain of what it is they are fighting for. National purposes have fallen more and more into the background; and the common purpose of enlightened mankind has taken their place. The counsels of plain men have become on all hands more simple and straightforward and more unified than the counsels of sophisticated men of affairs, who still retain the impression that they are playing a game of power and are playing for high stakes. That is why I have said that this is a people’s war, not a statesmen’s. Statesmen must follow the clarified common thought or be broken.22

‘Unless the Conference was prepared to follow the opinions of mankind,’ he said on his way to Paris, ‘and to express the will of the people rather than that of the leaders of the Conference, we should be involved in another break-up of the world.’23

Such conceptions did, in fact, play a conspicuous part in the work of the Conference. When the Italian Delegates proved recalcitrant in their claims to Fiume and the Adriatic coast, Wilson remained convinced that if he could appeal against the ‘leaders’ to the ‘people’, if only (as at the New Jersey election) he ‘could speak to enough of them’, the voice of reason must infallibly prevail. The communiqué to the Italian people, and the withdrawal of the Italian Delegation from Paris, were the result of this conviction. The problem of disarmament was approached in the same spirit. Once the enemy Powers had been disarmed by force, the voice of reason, speaking through public opinion, could be trusted to disarm the Allies. Both Wilson and Mr Lloyd George ‘felt that, if the German army was limited, France would have to follow suit, and that she could hardly maintain an immense army under those conditions’.24 And if anyone had paused to enquire on what compulsion France would have to disarm, the only answer could have been an appeal to the rational force of public opinion. Most important of all, the whole conception of the League of Nations was from the first closely bound up with the twin belief that public opinion was bound to prevail and that public opinion was the voice of reason. If ‘open covenants openly arrived at’ could be made the rule, the plain people could be relied on to see that the contents conformed to the requirements of that reason which was the highest morality. The new order must be based, not on ‘covenants of selfishness and compromise’ between governments, but on ‘the thought of the plain people here and everywhere throughout the world, the people who enjoy no privilege and have very simple and unsophisticated standards of right and wrong’.25 It must be ‘sustained by the organized opinion of mankind’.26

The ticklish problem of material sanctions was approached reluctantly from the American, and almost as reluctantly from the British, side. Like Taft, Anglo-Saxon opinion felt itself ‘very little concerned’ over this aspect of the matter; for the recognition of the necessity of sanctions was in itself a derogation from the utopian doctrine of the efficacy of rational public opinion. It was unthinkable that a unanimous verdict of the League should be defied; and even if by some mischance the verdict were not unanimous, ‘a majority report would probably be issued, and…this’, suggested Lord Cecil during the debates in Paris, ‘would be likely to carry great weight with the public opinion of the world’.27 The official British Commentary on the Covenant developed the same point of view:

The League [it declared] must continue to depend on the free consent, in the last resort, of its component States; this assumption is evident in nearly every article of the Covenant, of which the ultimate and most effective sanction must be the public opinion of the civilized world. If the nations of the future are in the main selfish, grasping and warlike, no instrument or machinery will restrain them. It is only possible to establish an organization which may make peaceful co-operation easy and hence customary, and to trust in the influence of custom to mould public opinion.

The sanctions provisions were slurred over, half apologetically and with a consolatory postscript:

Not the least important part of the pressure will be supplied by the publicity stipulated for in the procedure of settlement. The obscure issues from which international quarrels arise will be dragged out into the light of day and the creation of an informed public opinion made possible.28

When the House of Commons debated the ratification of the Versailles Treaty, Lord Cecil was the principal expositor of the League Covenant:

For the most part [he told the House] there is no attempt to rely on anything like a superstate; no attempt to rely upon force to carry out a decision of the Council or the Assembly of the League. That is almost impracticable as things stand now. What we rely upon is public opinion…and if we are wrong about it, then the whole thing is wrong.29

Addressing the Imperial Conference of 1923 on the subject of the League, Lord Cecil explained that ‘its method is not…the method of coercive government: it is a method of consent and its executive instrument is not force, but public opinion’.30 And when the first League Assembly met, Lord Cecil, as British Delegate, propounded the same philosophy from the tribune:

It is quite true that by far the most powerful weapon at the command of the League of Nations is not the economic or the military weapon or any other weapon of material force. By far the strongest weapon we have is the weapon of public opinion.31

Even the more sceptical and sophisticated Balfour, explaining the absence of sanctions from the Washington agreements of 1921, declared that ‘if any nation hereafter deliberately separates itself from the collective action we have taken in Washington in this year of grace, it will stand condemned before the world’;32 and it was one of the presuppositions of liberal democracy that such condemnation would be effective. But the argument that public opinion is the all-important weapon is two-edged; and in 1932, during the Manchurian crisis, the ingenious Sir John Simon used it to demonstrate that any other kind of action was superfluous. ‘The truth is’, he told the House of Commons, ‘that when public opinion, world opinion, is sufficiently unanimous to pronounce a firm moral condemnation, sanctions are not needed.’33 Given the Benthamite and Wilsonian premises, this answer was irrefutable. If public opinion had failed to curb Japan, then – as Lord Cecil had said in 1919 – ‘the whole thing is wrong’.

The nemesis of utopianism in international politics came rather suddenly. In September 1930, the President of Columbia University, Dr Nicholas Murray Butler, ventured on the ‘reasonably safe prediction that the next generation will see a constantly increasing respect for Cobden’s principles and point of view and a steadily growing endeavour more largely to give them practical effect in public policy’.34 On 10 September 1931, Lord Cecil told the Assembly of the League of Nations that ‘there has scarcely ever been a period in the world’s history when war seems less likely than it does at present’.35 On 18 September 1931, Japan opened her campaign in Manchuria; and in the following month, the last important country which had continued to adhere to the principle of free trade took the first steps towards the introduction of a general tariff.

From this point onwards, a rapid succession of events forced upon all serious thinkers a reconsideration of premises which were becoming more and more flagrantly divorced from reality. The Manchurian crisis had demonstrated that the ‘condemnation of international public opinion’, invoked by Taft and by so many after him, was a broken reed. In the United States, this conclusion was drawn with extreme reluctance. In 1932, an American Secretary of State still cautiously maintained that ‘the sanction of public opinion can be made one of the most potent sanctions of the world’.36 In September 1938, President Roosevelt based his intervention in the Czecho-Slovak crisis on the belief of the United States Government in ‘the moral force of public opinion’,37 and in April 1939, Mr Cordell Hull once again announced the conviction that ‘a public opinion, the most potent of all forces for peace, is more strongly developing throughout the world’.38 But in countries more directly menaced by international crisis, this consoling view no longer found many adherents; and the continued addition to it of American statesmen was regarded as an index of American unwillingness to resort to more potent weapons. Already in 1932, Mr Churchill taunted the League of Nations Union with ‘long-suffering and inexhaustible gullibility’ for continuing to preach this out-worn creed.39 Before long the group of intellectuals who had once stressed the relative unimportance of the ‘material’ weapons of the League began to insist loudly on economic and military sanctions as the necessary cornerstones of an international order. When Germany annexed Austria, Lord Cecil indignantly enquired whether the Prime Minister ‘holds that the use of material force is impracticable and that the League should cease to attempt “sanctions” and confine its efforts to moral force’.40 The answer might well have been that, if Neville Chamberlain did in fact hold this view, he could have learned it from Lord Cecil’s own earlier utterances.

Moreover, scepticism attacked not only the premise that public opinion is certain to prevail, but also the premise that public opinion is certain to be right. At the Peace Conference, it had been observed that statesmen were sometimes more reasonable and moderate in their demands than the public opinion which they were supposed to represent. Even Wilson himself once used – no doubt, in perfect sincerity – an argument which directly contradicted his customary thesis that reason can be made to prevail by appealing to ‘the plain people everywhere throughout the world’. In the League of Nations Commission of the Conference, the Japanese had raised the issue of race equality. ‘How can you treat on its merits in this quiet room’, enquired the President, ‘a question which will not be treated on its merits when it gets out of this room?’41 Later history provided many examples of this phenomenon. It became a commonplace for statesmen at Geneva and elsewhere to explain that they themselves had every desire to be reasonable, but that public opinion in their countries was inexorable; and though this plea was sometimes a pretext or a tactical manœuvῡre, there was often a solid substratum of reality beneath it. The prestige of public opinion correspondingly declined. ‘It does not help the conciliator, the arbitrator, the policeman or the judge’, wrote a well-known supporter of the League of Nations Union recently, ‘to be surrounded by a crowd emitting either angry or exulting cheers.’42 Woodrow Wilson’s ‘plain men throughout the world’, the spokesmen of ‘the common purpose of enlightened mankind’, had somehow transformed themselves into a disorderly mob emitting incoherent and unhelpful noises. It seemed undeniable that, in international affairs, public opinion was almost as often wrong-headed as it was impotent. But where so many of the presuppositions of 1919 were crumbling, the intellectual leaders of the utopian school stuck to their guns; and in Great Britain and the United States – and to a lesser degree in France – the rift between theory and practice assumed alarming dimensions. Armchair students of international affairs were unanimous about the kind of policy which ought to be followed, both in the political and in the economic field. Governments of many countries acted in a sense precisely contrary to this advice, and received the endorsement of public opinion at the polls.

The problem of diagnosis

In such disasters the obvious explanation is never far to seek. The able historian of the Communist International has noted that, in the history of that institution, ‘every failure – not objective failure, but the failure of the reality to comply with the utopia – supposes a traitor’.43 The principle has a wide application, and touches deep springs of human character. Statesmen of more than one country have been pilloried by disappointed utopians as wreckers of the international order. The few members of the school who have tried to go behind this simple anthropomorphic explanation hesitate between two alternative diagnoses. If mankind in its international relations has signally failed to achieve the rational good, it must either have been too stupid to understand that good, or too wicked to pursue it. Professor Zimmern leans to the hypothesis of stupidity, repeating almost word for word the argument of Buckle and Sir Norman Angell:

The obstacle in our path…is not in the moral sphere, but in the intellectual…It is not because men are ill-disposed that they cannot be educated into a world social consciousness. It is because they – let us be honest and say ‘we’ – are beings of conservative temper and limited intelligence.

The attempt to build a world order has failed not through ‘pride or ambition or greed’, but through ‘muddled thinking’.44 Professor Toynbee, on the other hand, sees the cause of the breakdown in human wickedness. In a single volume of the annual Survey of International Affairs, he accuses Italy of ‘positive, strong-willed, aggressive egotism’, Great Britain and France of ‘negative, weak-willed, cowardly egotism’, Western Christendom as a whole of a ‘sordid’ crime, and all the members of the League of Nations, except Abyssinia, of ‘covetousness’ or ‘cowardice’ (the choice is left to them), while the attitude of the Americans is merely ‘rather captious and perverse’.45 Some writers combined the charge of stupidity and the charge of wickedness. Much comment on international affairs was rendered tedious and sterile by incessant girding at a reality which refused to conform to utopian prescriptions.

The simplicity of these explanations seemed almost ludicrously disproportionate to the intensity and complexity of the international crisis.46 The impression made on the ordinary man was more accurately recorded in April 1938 in some words of Mr Anthony Eden:

It is utterly futile to imagine that we are involved in a European crisis which may pass as it has come. We are involved in a crisis of humanity all the world over. We are living in one of those great periods of history which are awe-inspiring in their responsibilities and in their consequences. Stupendous forces are loose, hurricane forces.47

It is not true, as Professor Toynbee believes, that we have been living in an exceptionally wicked age. It is not true, as Professor Zimmern implies, that we have been living in an exceptionally stupid one. Still less is it true, as Professor Lauterpacht more optimistically suggests, that what we have been experiencing is ‘a transient period of retrogression’ which should not be allowed unduly to colour our thought.48 It is a meaningless evasion to pretend that we have witnessed, not the failure of the League of Nations, but only the failure of those who refused to make it work. The breakdown of the nineteen-thirties was too overwhelming to be explained merely in terms of individual action or inaction. Its downfall involved the bankruptcy of the postulates on which it was based. The foundations of nineteenth-century belief are themselves under suspicion. It may be not that men stupidly or wickedly failed to apply right principles, but that the principles themselves were false or inapplicable. It may turn out to be untrue that if men reason rightly about international politics they will also act rightly, or that right reasoning about one’s own or one’s nation’s interests is the road to an international paradise. If the assumptions of nineteenth-century liberalism are in fact untenable, it need not surprise us that the utopia of the international theorists made so little impression on reality. But if they are untenable today, we shall also have to explain why they found such widespread acceptance, and inspired such splendid achievements, in the nineteenth century.

Notes

1.

|   |

While this is the form of utopianism which has been predominant for the past three centuries, and which still prevails (though perhaps with diminishing force) in English-speaking countries, it would be rash to assert that individualism and rationalism are necessary attributes to utopian thought. Fascism contained elements of a utopianism which was anti-individualist and irrational. These qualities were already latent in the utopian aspects of Leninism – and perhaps even of Marxism.

2.

|   |

Bentham, Works, ed. Bowring, i. p. 31.

3.

|   |

Bentham, Works, ed. Bowring, viii. p. 561.

4.

|   |

James Mill, The Liberty of the Press, pp. 22–3.

5.

|   |

J. S. Bury, The Idea of Progress, p. 131.

6.

|   |

Comte, Cours de Philosophie Positive, Lecture LXI.

7.

|   |

Buckle, History of Civilisation (World’s Classics ed.), i. pp. 151–2.

8.

|   |

Quoted in Angell, Foundations of International Polity, p. 224. Internal evidence suggests that the passage was written by Sir Norman Angell himself.

9.

|   |

R. H. S. Crossman in J. P. Mayer, Political Thought, p. 202.

10.

|   |

New Year’s Eve broadcast from Radio-Nations, Geneva: The Times, 1 January 1938.

11.

|   |

The Covenant of the League of Nations and a Commentary Thereon, Cmd 151 (1919), p. 12. ‘The great strength of the Covenant’, said the British Government some years later, ‘lies in the measure of discretion which it allows to the Council and Assembly in dealing with future contingencies which may have no parallel in history and which therefore cannot all of them be foreseen in advance’ (League of Nations: Official Journal, May 1928, p. 703).

12.

|   |

The defection of the United States upset this balance, and left four major confronted with four minor Powers. Subsequent increases in membership, which have taken place at frequent intervals since 1923, gave a permanent preponderance to the minor Powers. The Council, in becoming more ‘representative’, lost much of its effectiveness as a political instrument. Reality was sacrificed to an abstract principle. It should be added that the prudent Swiss Delegate foresaw this result when the first increase was mooted in 1922 (League of Nations: Third Assembly, First Committee, pp. 37–8).

13.

|   |

By a curious irony, this development was strongly encouraged by a group of American intellectuals; and some European enthusiasts imagined that, by following this course, they would propitiate American opinion. The rift between the theory of the intellectuals and the practice of the government, which developed in Great Britain from 1932 onwards, began in the United States in 1919.

14.

|   |

J. Fischer-Williams, Some Aspects of the Covenant of the League of Nations, p. 238.

15.

|   |

Winston Churchill, Arms and the Covenant, p. 43.

16.

|   |

Quoted in Toynbee, Survey of International Affairs, 1935, ii, p. 448.

17.

|   |

B. Russell in Atlantic Monthly, clix. (February 1937), p. 155.

18.

|   |

League of Nations: Fifth Assembly, p. 497.

19.

|   |

W. Taft, The United States and Peace, p. 150.

20.

|   |

The Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: The New Democracy, ed. R. S. Baker, i. p. 206.

21.

|   |

R. S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson: Life and Letters, iii. p. 173.

22.

|   |

The Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: War and Peace, ed. R. S. Baker, i. p. 259.

23.

|   |

Intimate Papers of Colonel House, ed. C. Seymour, iv. p. 291.

24.

|   |

D. Lloyd George, The Truth about the Treaties, i. p. 187.

25.

|   |

The Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: War and Peace, ed. R. S. Baker, i. p. 133.

26.

|   |

Ibid., i. p. 234.

27.

|   |

Miller, The Drafting of the Covenant, ii. p. 64.

28.

|   |

The Covenant of the League of Nations with a Commentary Thereon, Cmd 151, pp. 12, 16.

29.

|   |

House of Commons, 21 July 1919: Official Report, cols. 990, 992.

30.

|   |

Imperial Conference of 1923, Cmd 1987, p. 44.

31.

|   |

League of Nations: First Assembly, p. 395.

32.

|   |

Quoted in Zimmern, The League of Nations and the Rule of Law, p. 399.

33.

|   |

House of Commons, 22 March 1932: Official Report, col. 923.

34.

|   |

N. M. Butler, The Path to Peace, p. xii.

35.

|   |

League of Nations: Twelfth Assembly, p. 59.

36.

|   |

Mr Stimson to the Council of Foreign Relations on 8 August 1932 (New York Times, 9 August 1932).

37.

|   |

‘Believing, as this government does, in the moral force of public opinion…’ (Sumner Welles in State Department Press Releases, 8 October 1938, p. 237).

38.

|   |

The Times, 18 April 1939.

39.

|   |

Winston Churchill, Arms and the Covenant, p. 36.

40.

|   |

Daily Telegraph, 24 March 1938.

41.

|   |

Miller, The Drafting of the Covenant, ii. p. 701.

42.

|   |

Lord Allen of Hurtwood, The Times, 30 May 1938.

43.

|   |

F. Borkenau, The Communist International, p. 179.

44.

|   |

Neutrality and Collective Security (Harris Foundation Lectures: Chicago, 1936), pp. 8, 18.

45.

|   |

Survey of International Affairs, 1935, ii. pp. 2, 89, 96, 219–20, 480.

46.

|   |

As a recent writer has said of the French eighteenth-century rationalists, ‘their superficiality lay in a shocking exaggeration of the simplicity of the problem’ (Sabine, A History of Political Theory, p. 551).

47.

|   |

Anthony Eden, Foreign Affairs, p. 275.

48.

|   |

International Affairs, xvii. (September-October 1938), p. 712.

CHAPTER FIVE

The Realist Critique

The foundations of realism

For reasons explained in a previous chapter, realism enters the field far behind utopianism and by way of reaction from it. The thesis that ‘justice is the right of the stranger’ was, indeed, familiar in the Hellenic world. But it never represented anything more than the protest of an uninfluential minority, puzzled by the divergence between political theory and political practice. Under the supremacy of the Roman Empire, and later of the Catholic Church, the problem could hardly arise; for the political good, first of the empire, then of the church, could be regarded as identical with moral good. It was only with the break-up of the mediaeval system that the divergence between political theory and political practice became acute and challenging. Machiavelli is the first important political realist.

Machiavelli’s starting-point is a revolt against the utopianism of current political thought:

It being my intention to write a thing which shall be useful to him who apprehends it, it appears to me more appropriate to follow up the real truth of a matter than the imagination of it; for many have pictured republics and principalities which in fact have never been seen and known, because how one lives is so far distant from how one ought to live that he who neglects what is done for what ought to be done sooner effects his ruin than his preservation.

The three essential tenets implicit in Machiavelli’s doctrine are the foundation-stones of the realist philosophy. In the first place, history is a sequence of cause and effect, whose course can be analysed and understood by intellectual effort, but not (as the utopians believe) directed by ‘imagination’. Secondly, theory does not (as the utopians assume) create practice, but practice theory. In Machiavelli’s words, ‘good counsels, whencesoever they come, are born of the wisdom of the prince, and not the wisdom of the prince from good counsels’. Thirdly, politics are not (as the utopians pretend) a function of ethics, but ethics of politics. Men ‘are kept honest by constraint’. Machiavelli recognized the importance of morality, but thought that there could be no effective morality where there was no effective authority. Morality is the product of power.1

The extraordinary vigour and vitality of Machiavelli’s challenge to orthodoxy may be attested by the fact that, more than four centuries after he wrote, the most conclusive way of discrediting a political opponent is still to describe him as a disciple of Machiavelli.2 Bacon was one of the first to praise him for ‘saying openly and without hypocrisy what men are in the habit of doing, not what they ought to do’.3 Henceforth no political thinker could ignore him. In France Bodin, in England Hobbes, in The Netherlands Spinoza, professed to find a compromise between the new doctrine and the conception of a ‘law of nature’ constituting a supreme ethical standard. But all three were in substance realists; and the age of Newton for the first time conceived the possibility of a physical science of politics.4 The work of Bodin and Hobbes, writes Professor Laski, was ‘to separate ethics from politics, and to complete by theoretical means the division which Machiavelli had effected on practical grounds’.5 ‘Before the names of Just and Unjust can have place’, said Hobbes, ‘there must be some coercive power.’6 Spinoza believed that practical statesmen had contributed more to the understanding of politics than men of theory ‘and, above all, theologians’; for ‘they have put themselves to the school of experience, and have therefore taught nothing which does not bear upon our practical needs’.7 In anticipation of Hegel, Spinoza declares that ‘every man does what he does according to the laws of his nature and to the highest right of nature’.8 The way is thus opened for determinism; and ethics become, in the last analysis, the study of reality.

Modern realism differs, however, in one important respect from that of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. Both utopianism and realism accepted and incorporated in their philosophies the eighteenth-century belief in progress, with the curious and somewhat paradoxical result that realism became in appearance more ‘progressive’ than utopianism. Utopianism grafted its belief in progress on to its belief in an absolute ethical standard, which remained ex hypothesi static. Realism, having no such sheet anchor, became more and more dynamic and relativist. Progress became part of the inner essence of the historical process; and mankind was moving forward towards a goal which was left undefined, or was differently defined by different philosophers. The ‘historical school’ of realists had its home in Germany, and its development is traced through the great names of Hegel and Marx. But no country in Western Europe, and no branch of thought, was immune from its influence in the middle and later years of the nineteenth century; and this development, while it has freed realism from the pessimistic colouring imparted to it by thinkers like Machiavelli and Hobbes, has thrown its determinist character into stronger relief.

The idea of causation in history is as old as the writing of history itself. But so long as the belief prevailed that human affairs were subject to the continuous supervision and occasional intervention of a Divine Providence, no philosophy of history based on a regular relationship of cause and effect was likely to be evolved. The substitution of reason for Divine Providence enabled Hegel to produce, for the first time, a philosophy based on the conception of a rational historical process. Hegel, while assuming a regular and orderly process, was content to find its directing force in a metaphysical abstraction – the Zeitgeist. But once the historical conception of reality had established itself, it was a short step to substitute for the abstract Zeitgeist some concrete material force. The economic interpretation of history was not invented, but developed and popularized, by Marx. About the same time Buckle propounded a geographical interpretation of history which convinced him that human affairs were ‘permeated by one glorious principle of universal and undeviating regularity’;9 and this has been revived in the form of the science of Geopolitik, whose inventor describes geography as ‘a political categorical imperative’.10 Spengler believed that events were determined by quasibiological laws governing the growth and decline of civilizations. More eclectic thinkers interpret history as the product of a variety of material factors, and the policy of a group or nation as a reflexion of all the material factors which make up the group or national interest. ‘Foreign policies’, said Mr Hughes during his tenure of office as American Secretary of State, ‘are not built upon abstractions. They are the result of national interest arising from some immediate exigency or standing out vividly in historical perspective’.11 Any such interpretation of reality, whether in terms of a Zeitgeist, or of economics or geography, or of ‘historical perspective’, is in its last analysis deterministic. Marx (though, having a programme of action, he could not be a rigid and consistent determinist) believed in ‘tendencies which work out with an iron necessity towards an inevitable goal’.12 ‘Politics’, wrote Lenin, ‘have their own objective logic independent of the prescriptions of this or that individual or party.’13 In January 1918, he described his belief in the coming socialist revolutions in Europe as ‘a scientific prediction’.14

On the ‘scientific’ hypothesis of the realists, reality is thus identified with the whole course of historical evolution, whose laws it is the business of the philosopher to investigate and reveal. There can be no reality outside the historical process. ‘To conceive of history as evolution and progress’, writes Croce, ‘implies accepting it as necessary in all its parts, and therefore denying validity to judgements on it.’15 Condemnation of the past on ethical grounds has no meaning; for in Hegel’s words, ‘philosophy transfigures the real which appears unjust into the rational’.16 What was, is right. History cannot be judged except by historical standards. It is significant that our historical judgements, except those relating to a past which we can ourselves remember as the present, always appear to start from the presupposition that things could not have turned out otherwise than they did. It is recorded that Venizelos, on reading in Fisher’s History of Europe that the Greek invasion of Asia Minor in 1919 was a mistake, smiled ironically and said: ‘Every enterprise that does not succeed is a mistake.’17 If Wat Tyler’s rebellion had succeeded, he would be an English national hero. If the American War of Independence had ended in disaster, the Founding Fathers of the United States would be briefly recorded in history as a gang of turbulent and unscrupulous fanatics. Nothing succeeds like success. ‘World history’, in the famous phrase which Hegel borrowed from Schiller, ‘is the world court.’ The popular paraphrase ‘Might is Right’ is misleading only if we attach too restricted a meaning to the word ‘Might’. History creates rights, and therefore right. The doctrine of the survival of the fittest proves that the survivor was, in fact, the fittest to survive. Marx does not seem to have maintained that the victory of the proletariat was just in any other sense than that it was historically inevitable. Lukacs was a consistent, though perhaps indiscreet, Marxist when he based the ‘right’ of the proletariat on its ‘historical mission’.18 Hitler believed in the historical mission of the German people.

The relativity of thought

The outstanding achievement of modern realism, however, has been to reveal, not merely the determinist aspects of the historical process, but the relative and pragmatic character of thought itself. In the last fifty years, thanks mainly though not wholly to the influence of Marx, the principles of the historical school have been applied to the analysis of thought; and the foundations of a new science have been laid, principally by German thinkers, under the name of the ‘sociology of knowledge’. The realist has thus been enabled to demonstrate that the intellectual theories and ethical standards of utopianism, far from being the expression of absolute and a priori principles, are historically conditioned, being both products of circumstances and interests and weapons framed for the furtherance of interests. ‘Ethical notions’, as Mr Bertrand Russell has remarked, ‘are very seldom a cause, but almost always an effect, a means of claiming universal legislative authority for our own preference, not, as we fondly imagine, the actual ground of those preferences.’19 This is by far the most formidable attack which utopianism has to face; for here the very foundations of its belief are undermined by the realist critique.

In a general way, the relativity of thought has long been recognized. As early as the seventeenth century Bishop Burnet expounded the relativist view as cogently, if not as pungently, as Marx:

As to the late Civil Wars, ‘tis pretty well known what notions of government went current in those days. When monarchy was to be subverted we knew what was necessary to justify the fact; and then, because it was convenient for the purpose, it was undoubtedly true in the nature of things that government had its original from the people, and the prince was only their trustee. . . . But afterwards, when monarchy took its place again . . . another notion of government came into fashion. Then government had its original entirely from God, and the prince was accountable to none but Him. . . . And now, upon another turn of things, when people have a liberty to speak out, a new set of notions is advanced; now passive obedience is all a mistake, and instead of being a duty to suffer oppression, ‘tis a glorious act to resist it: and instead of leaving injuries to be redressed by God, we have a natural right to relieve ourselves.20

In modern times, the recognition of this phenomenon has become fairly general. ‘Belief, and to speak fairly, honest belief,’ wrote Dicey of the divisions of opinion in the nineteenth century about slavery, ‘was to a great extent the result not of argument, not even of direct self-interest, but of circumstances. . . . Circumstances are the creators of most men’s opinions.’21 Marx narrowed down this somewhat vague conception, declaring that all thought was conditioned by the economic interest and social status of the thinker. This view was perhaps unduly restrictive. In particular Marx, who denied the existence of ‘national’ interests, underestimated the potency of nationalism as a force conditioning the thought of the individual. But the peculiar concentration which he applied to the principle served to popularize it and drive it home. The relativity of thought to the interests and circumstances of the thinker has been far more extensively recognized and understood since Marx wrote.

The principle has an extremely wide field of application. It has become a commonplace to say that theories do not mould the course of events, but are invented to explain them. ‘Empire precedes imperialism.’22 Eight-eenth-century England ‘put into practice the policy of laissez-faire before it found a justification, or even an apparent justification, in the new doctrine’;23 and ‘the virtual break-up of laissez-faire as a body of doctrine . . . has followed, and not preceded, the decline of laissez-faire in the real world’.24 The theory of ‘socialism in a single country’ promulgated in Soviet Russia in 1924 was manifestly a product of the failure of Soviet régimes to establish themselves in other countries.

But the development of abstract theory is often influenced by events which have no essential connexion with it at all.

In the story of political thought [writes a modern social thinker] events have been no less potent than arguments. The failure and success of institutions, the victories and defeats of countries identified with certain principles have repeatedly brought new strength and resolution to the adherents or opponents of these principles as the case might be in all lands. . . . Philosophy as it exists on earth is the word of philosophers who, authority tells us, suffer as much from toothache as other mortals, and are, like others, open to the impression of near and striking events and to the seductions of intellectual fashion.25

Germany’s dramatic rise to power in the sixties and seventies of the last century was impressive enough to make the leading British philosophers of the next generation – Caird, T. H. Green, Bosanquet, McTaggart – ardent Hegelians. Thereafter, the Kaiser’s telegram to Kruger and the German naval programme spread the conviction among British thinkers that Hegel was a less good philosopher than had been supposed; and since 1914 no British philosopher of repute has ventured to sail under the Hegelian flag. After 1870, Stubbs and Freeman put early English history on a sound Teutonic basis, while even in France Fustel de Coulanges had an uphill struggle to defend the Latin origins of French civilization. During the past thirty years, English historians have been furtively engaged in making the Teutonic origins of England as inconspicuous as possible.

Nor is it only professional thinkers who are subject to such influences. Popular opinion is not less markedly dominated by them. The frivolity and immorality of French life was an established dogma in nineteenth-century Britain, which still remembered Napoleon. ‘When I was young,’ writes Mr Bertrand Russell, ‘the French ate frogs and were called “froggies”, but they apparently abandoned this practice when we concluded our entente with them in 1904 – at any rate, I have never heard it mentioned since that date.’26 Some years later, ‘the gallant little Jap’ of 1905 underwent a converse metamorphosis into ‘the Prussian of the East’. In the nineteenth century, it was a commonplace of British opinion that Germans were efficient and enlightened, and Russians backward and barbarous. About 1910, it was ascertained that Germans (who turned out to be mostly Prussians) were coarse, brutal and narrow-minded, and that Russians had a Slav soul. The vogue of Russian literature in Great Britain, which set in about the same time, was a direct outcome of the political rapprochement with Russia. The vogue of Marxism in Great Britain and France, which began on a modest scale after the success of the Bolshevik revolution in Russia, rapidly gathered momentum, particularly among intellectuals, after 1934, when it was discovered that Soviet Russia was a potential military ally against Germany. It is symptomatic that most people, when challenged, will indignantly deny that they form their opinions in this way; for as Acton long ago observed, ‘few discoveries are more irritating than those which expose the pedigree of ideas’.27 The conditioning of thought is necessarily a subconscious process.

The adjustment of thought to purpose

Thought is not merely relative to the circumstances and interests of the thinker: it is also pragmatic in the sense that it is directed to the fulfilment of his purposes. For the realist, as a witty writer has put it, truth is ‘no more than the perception of discordant experience pragmatically adjusted for a particular purpose and for the time being’.28 The purposeful character of thought has been discussed in a previous chapter; and a few examples will suffice here to illustrate the importance of this phenomenon in international politics.

Theories designed to discredit an enemy or potential enemy are one of the commonest forms of purposeful thinking. To depict one’s enemies or one’s prospective victims as inferior beings in the sight of God has been a familiar technique at any rate since the days of the Old Testament. Racial theories, ancient and modern, belong to this category; for the rule of one people or class over another is always justified by a belief in the mental and moral inferiority of the ruled. In such theories, sexual abnormality and sexual offences are commonly imputed to the discredited race or group. Sexual depravity is imputed by the white American to the negro; by the white South African to the Kaffir; by the Anglo-Indian to the Hindu; and by the Nazi German to the Jew. The most popular and most absurd of the charges levelled against the Bolsheviks in the early days of the Russian revolution was that they advocated sexual promiscuity. Atrocity stories, among which offences of a sexual character predominate, are the familiar product of war. On the eve of their invasion of Abyssinia, the Italians issued an official Green Book of Abyssinian atrocities. ‘The Italian Government,’ as the Abyssinian delegate at Geneva correctly observed, ‘having resolved to conquer and destroy Ethiopia, begins by giving Ethiopia a bad name.’29

But the phenomenon also appears in less crude forms which sometimes enable it to escape detection. The point was well made by Crowe in a Foreign Office minute of March 1908:

The German (formerly Prussian) Government has always been most remarkable for the pains it takes to create a feeling of intense and holy hatred against a country with which it contemplates the possibility of war. It is undoubtedly in this way that the frantic hatred of England as a monster of personified selfishness and greed and absolute want of conscience, which now animates Germany, has been nursed and fed.30

The diagnosis is accurate and penetrating. But it is strange that so acute a mind as Crowe’s should not have perceived that he himself was at this time performing, for the limited audience of statesmen and officials to which he had access, precisely the same operation of which he accused the German Government; for a perusal of his memoranda and minutes of the period reveals an able, but transparent, attempt to ‘create a feeling of intense and holy hatred’ against his own country’s future enemy – a curious instance of our promptness to detect the conditioned or purposeful character of other people’s thought, while assuming that our own is wholly objective.

The converse of this propagation of theories designed to throw moral discredit on an enemy is the propagation of theories reflecting moral credit on oneself and one’s own policies. Bismarck records the remark made to him by Walewski, the French Foreign Minister, in 1857, that it was the business of a diplomat to cloak the interests of his country in the language of universal justice. More recently, Mr Churchill told the House of Commons that ‘there must be a moral basis for British rearmament and foreign policy’.31 It is rare, however, for modern statesmen to express themselves with this frankness; and in contemporary British and American politics, the most powerful influence has been wielded by those more utopian statesmen who are sincerely convinced that policy is deduced from ethical principles, not ethical principles from policy. The realist is nevertheless obliged to uncover the hollowness of this conviction. ‘The right’, said Woodrow Wilson to the United States Congress in 1917, ‘is more precious than peace.’32 ‘Peace comes before all,’ said Briand ten years later to the League of Nations Assembly, ‘peace comes even before justice.’33 Considered as ethical principles, both these contradictory pronouncements are tenable and could muster respectable support. Are we therefore to believe that we are dealing with a clash of ethical standards, and that if Wilson’s and Briand’s policies differed it was because they deduced them from opposite principles? No serious student of politics will entertain this belief. The most cursory examination shows that the principles were deduced from the policies, not the policies from the principles. In 1917, Wilson had decided on the policy of war with Germany, and he proceeded to clothe that policy in the appropriate garment of righteousness. In 1928 Briand was fearful of attempts made in the name of justice to disturb a peace settlement favourable to France; and he had no more difficulty than Wilson in finding the moral phraseology which fitted his policy. It would be irrelevant to discuss this supposed difference of principles on ethical grounds. The principles merely reflected different national policies framed to meet different conditions.

The double process of morally discrediting the policy of a potential enemy and morally justifying one’s own may be abundantly illustrated from the discussions of disarmament between the two wars. The experience of the Anglo-Saxon Powers, whose naval predominance had been threatened by the submarine, provided an ample opportunity of denouncing the immorality of this new weapon. ‘Civilization demands’, wrote the naval adviser to the American Delegation at the Peace Conference, ‘that naval warfare be placed on a higher plane’ by the abolition of the submarine.34 Unfortunately the submarine was regarded as a convenient weapon by the weaker French, Italian and Japanese navies; and this particular demand of civilization could not therefore be complied with. A distinction of a more sweeping character was established by Lord Cecil in a speech to the General Council of the League of Nations Union in 1922:

The general peace of the world will not be materially secured merely by naval disarmament. . . . If all the maritime Powers were to disarm, or drastically limit their armaments, I am not at all sure that would not increase the danger of war rather than decrease it, because the naval arm is mainly defensive; the offensive must be to a large extent the military weapon.35

The inspiration of regarding one’s own vital armaments as defensive and beneficent and those of other nations as offensive and wicked proved particularly fruitful. Exactly ten years later, three commissions of the Disarmament Conference spent many weeks in a vain endeavour to classify armaments as ‘offensive’ and ‘defensive’. Delegates of all nations showed extraordinary ingenuity in devising arguments, supposedly based on pure objective theory, to prove that the armaments on which they chiefly relied were defensive, while those of potential rivals were essentially offensive. Similar attitudes have been taken up in regard to economic ‘armaments’. In the latter part of the nineteenth century – and in a lesser degree down to 1931 – protective tariffs were commonly regarded in Great Britain as immoral. After 1931 straight tariffs regained their innocence, but barter agreements, industrial (though not agricultural) quotas, exchange controls and other weapons employed by Continental states were still tainted with immorality. Down to 1930, successive revisions of the United States tariff had almost invariably been upward; and American economists, in other respects staunch upholders of laissez-faire, had almost invariably treated tariffs as legitimate and laudable. But the change in the position of the United States from a debtor to a creditor Power, combined with the reversal of British economic policy, altered the picture; and the reduction of tariff barriers has come to be commonly identified by American spokesmen with the cause of international morality.

National interest and the universal good

The realist should not, however, linger over the infliction of these pinpricks through chinks in the utopian defences. His task is to bring down the whole cardboard structure of utopian thought by exposing the hollowness of the material out of which it is built. The weapon of the relativity of thought must be used to demolish the utopian concept of a fixed and absolute standard by which policies and actions can be judged. If theories are revealed as a reflexion of practice and principles of political needs, this discovery will apply to the fundamental theories and principles of the utopian creed, and not least to the doctrine of the harmony of interests which is its essential postulate.

It will not be difficult to show that the utopian, when he preaches the doctrine of the harmony of interests, is innocently and unconsciously adopting Walewski’s maxim, and clothing his own interest in the guise of a universal interest for the purpose of imposing it on the rest of the world. ‘Men come easily to believe that arrangements agreeable to themselves are beneficial to others,’ as Dicey observed;36 and theories of the public good, which turn out on inspection to be an elegant disguise for some particular interest, are as common in international as in national affairs. The utopian, however eager he may be to establish an absolute standard, does not argue that it is the duty of his country, in conformity with that standard, to put the interest of the world at large before its own interest; for that would be contrary to his theory that the interest of all coincides with the interest of each. He argues that what is best for the world is best for his country, and then reverses the argument to read that what is best for his country is best for the world, the two propositions being, from the utopian standpoint, identical; and this unconscious cynicism of the contemporary utopian has proved a far more effective diplomatic weapon than the deliberate and self-conscious cynicism of a Walewski or a Bismarck. British writers of the past half-century have been particularly eloquent supporters of the theory that the maintenance of British supremacy is the performance of a duty to mankind. ‘If Great Britain has turned itself into a coal-shed and blacksmith’s forge,’ remarked The Times ingenuously in 1885, ‘it is for the behoof of mankind as well as its own.’37 The following extract is typical of a dozen which might be culled from memoirs of public men of the period:

I have but one great object in this world, and that is to maintain the greatness of the Empire. But apart from my John Bull sentiment upon the point, I firmly believe that in doing so I work in the cause of Christianity, of peace, of civilisation, and the happiness of the human race generally.38

‘I contend that we are the first race in the world,’ wrote Cecil Rhodes, ‘and that the more of the world we inhabit the better it is for the human race.’39 In 1891, the most popular and brilliant journalist of the day, W. T. Stead, founded the Review of Reviews. ‘We believe in God, in England and in Humanity,’ ran the editorial manifesto in its opening number. ‘The English-speaking race is one of the chief of God’s chosen agents for executing coming improvements in the lot of mankind.’40 An Oxford professor was convinced in 1912 that the secret of Britain’s history was that ‘in fighting for her own independence she has been fighting for the freedom of Europe, and that the service thus rendered to Europe and to mankind has carried with it the possibility of that larger service to which we give the name Empire’.41

The first world war carried this conviction to a pitch of emotional frenzy. A bare catalogue, culled from the speeches of British statesmen, of the services which British belligerency was rendering to humanity would fill many pages. In 1917, Balfour told the New York Chamber of Commerce that ‘since August 1914, the fight has been for the highest spiritual advantages of mankind, without a petty thought or ambition’.42 The Peace Conference and its sequel temporarily discredited these professions and threw some passing doubt on the belief in British supremacy as one of the moral assets of mankind. But the period of disillusionment and modesty was short. Moments of international tension, and especially moments when the possibility of war appears on the horizon, always stimulate this identification of national interest with morality. At the height of the Abyssinian crisis, the Archbishop of Canterbury admonished the French public through an interview in a Paris newspaper:

We are animated by moral and spiritual considerations. I do not think I am departing from my role by contributing towards the clearing up of this misunderstanding . . .

    It is . . . no egoist interest that is driving us forward, and no consideration of interest should keep you behind.43

In the following year, Professor Toynbee was once more able to discover that the security of the British Empire ‘was also the supreme interest of the whole world’.44 In 1937, Lord Cecil spoke to the General Council of the League of Nations Union of ‘our duty to our country, to our Empire and to humanity at large’, and quoted:

Not once nor twice in our rough island story

The path of duty is the way to glory.45

An Englishman, as Mr Bernard Shaw remarks in The Man of Destiny, ‘never forgets that the nation which lets its duty get on to the opposite side to its interest is lost’. It is not surprising that an American critic should recently have described the British as ‘Jesuits lost to the theological but gained for the political realm’,46 or that a former Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs should have commented, long before these recent manifestations, on ‘that precious gift bestowed upon the British people – the possession of writers and clergymen able in perfect good faith to advance the highest moral reasons for the most concrete diplomatic action, with inevitable moral profit to England’.47

In recent times, the same phenomenon has become endemic in the United States. The story of how McKinley prayed for divine guidance and decided to annex the Philippines is a classic of modern American history; and this annexation was the occasion of a popular outburst of moral self-approval hitherto more familiar in the foreign policy of Great Britain than of the United States. Theodore Roosevelt, who believed more firmly than any previous American President in the doctrine L’état, c’est moi, carried the process a step further. The following curious dialogue occurred in his cross-examination during a libel action brought against him in 1915 by a Tammany leader:

Query: How did you know that substantial justice was done?

ROOSEVELT: Because I did it, because . . . I was doing my best.

Query: You mean to say that, when you do a thing, thereby substantial justice is done.

ROOSEVELT: I do. When I do a thing, I do it so as to do substantial justice. I mean just that.48

Woodrow Wilson was less naïvely egotistical, but more profoundly confident of the identity of American policy and universal justice. After the bombardment of Vera Cruz in 1914, he assured the world that ‘the United States had gone down to Mexico to serve mankind’.49 During the first world war, he advised American naval cadets ‘not only always to think first of America, but always, also, to think first of humanity’ – a feat rendered slightly less difficult by his explanation that the United States had been ‘founded for the benefit of humanity’.50 Shortly before the entry of the United States into the war, in an address to the Senate on war aims, he stated the identification still more categorically: ‘These are American principles, American policies . . . They are the principles of mankind and must prevail.’51

It will be observed that utterances of this character proceed almost exclusively from Anglo-Saxon statesmen and writers. It is true that when a prominent National Socialist asserted that ‘anything that benefits the German people is right, anything that harms the German people is wrong’,52 he was merely propounding the same identification of national interest with universal right which had already been established for English-speaking countries by Wilson, Professor Toynbee, Lord Cecil and many others. But when the claim is translated into a foreign language, the note seems forced, and the identification unconvincing, even to the peoples concerned. Two explanations are commonly given of this curious discrepancy. The first explanation, which is popular in English-speaking countries, is that the policies of the English-speaking nations are in fact more virtuous and disinterested than those of Continental states, so that Wilson and Professor Toynbee and Lord Cecil are, broadly speaking, right when they identify the American and British national interest with the interest of mankind. The second explanation, which is popular in Continental countries, is that the English-speaking peoples are past masters in the art of concealing their selfish national interests in the guise of the general good, and that this kind of hypocrisy is a special and characteristic peculiarity of the Anglo-Saxon mind.

It seems unnecessary to accept either of these heroic attempts to cut the knot. The solution is a simple one. Theories of social morality are always the product of a dominant group which identifies itself with the community as a whole, and which possesses facilities denied to subordinate groups or individuals for imposing its view of life on the community. Theories of international morality are, for the same reason and in virtue of the same process, the product of dominant nations or groups of nations. For the past hundred years, and more especially since 1918, the English-speaking peoples have formed the dominant group in the world; and current theories of international morality have been designed to perpetuate their supremacy and expressed in the idiom peculiar to them. France, retaining something of her eighteenth-century tradition and restored to a position of dominance for a short period after 1918, has played a minor part in the creation of current international morality, mainly through her insistence on the role of law in the moral order. Germany, never a dominant Power and reduced to helplessness after 1918, has remained for these reasons outside the charmed circle of creators of international morality. Both the view that the English-speaking peoples are monopolists of international morality and the view that they are consummate international hypocrites may be reduced to the plain fact that the current canons of international virtue have, by a natural and inevitable process, been mainly created by them.

The realist critique of the harmony of interests

The doctrine of the harmony of interests yields readily to analysis in terms of this principle. It is the natural assumption of a prosperous and privileged class, whose members have a dominant voice in the community and are therefore naturally prone to identify its interests with their own. In virtue of this identification, any assailant of the interests of the dominant group is made to incur the odium of assailing the alleged common interest of the whole community, and is told that in making this assault he is attacking his own higher interests. The doctrine of the harmony of interests thus serves as an ingenious moral device invoked, in perfect sincerity, by privileged groups in order to justify and maintain their dominant position. But a further point requires notice. The supremacy within the community of the privileged group may be, and often is, so overwhelming that there is, in fact, a sense in which its interests are those of the community, since its well-being necessarily carries with it some measure of well-being for other members of the community, and its collapse would entail the collapse of the community as a whole. In so far, therefore, as the alleged natural harmony of interests has any reality, it is created by the overwhelming power of the privileged group, and is an excellent illustration of the Machiavellian maxim that morality is the product of power. A few examples will make this analysis of the doctrine of the harmony of interests clear.

In the nineteenth century, the British manufacturer or merchant, having discovered that laissez-faire promoted his own prosperity, was sincerely convinced that it also promoted British prosperity as a whole. Nor was this alleged harmony of interests between himself and the community entirely fictious. The predominance of the manufacturer and the merchant was so overwhelming that there was a sense in which an identity between their prosperity and British prosperity as a whole could be correctly asserted. From this it was only a short step to argue that a worker on strike, in damaging the prosperity of the British manufacturer, was damaging British prosperity as a whole, and thereby damaging his own, so that he could be plausibly denounced by the predecessors of Professor Toynbee as immoral and by the predecessors of Professor Zimmern as muddle-headed. Moreover, there was a sense in which this argument was perfectly correct. Nevertheless, the doctrine of the harmony of interests and of solidarity between the classes must have seemed a bitter mockery to the underprivileged worker, whose inferior status and insignificant stake in ‘British prosperity’ were consecrated by it; and presently he was strong enough to force the abandonment of laissez-faire and the substitution for it of the ‘social service state’, which implicitly denies the natural harmony of interests and sets out to create a new harmony by artificial means.

The same analysis may be applied in international relations. British nineteenth-century statesmen, having discovered that free trade promoted British prosperity, were sincerely convinced that, in doing so, it also promoted the prosperity of the world as a whole. British predominance in world trade was at that time so overwhelming that there was a certain undeniable harmony between British interests and the interests of the world. British prosperity flowed over into other countries, and a British economic collapse would have meant worldwide ruin. British free traders could and did argue that protectionist countries were not only egotistically damaging the prosperity of the world as a whole, but were stupidly damaging their own, so that their behaviour was both immoral and muddle-headed. In British eyes, it was irrefutably proved that international trade was a single whole, and flourished or slumped together. Nevertheless, this alleged international harmony of interests seemed a mockery to those underprivileged nations whose inferior status and insignificant stake in international trade were consecrated by it. The revolt against it destroyed that overwhelming British preponderance which had provided a plausible basis for the theory. Economically, Great Britain in the nineteenth century was dominant enough to make a bold bid to impose on the world her own conception of international economic morality. When competition of all against all replaced the domination of the world market by a single Power, conceptions of international economic morality necessarily became chaotic.

Politically, the alleged community of interest in the maintenance of peace, whose ambiguous character has already been discussed, is capitalized in the same way by a dominant nation or group of nations. Just as the ruling class in a community prays for domestic peace, which guarantees its own security and predominance, and denounces class war, which might threaten them, so international peace becomes a special vested interest of predominant Powers. In the past, Roman and British imperialism were commended to the world in the guise of the pax Romana and the pax Britannica. To-day, when no single Power is strong enough to dominate the world, and supremacy is vested in a group of nations, slogans like ‘collective security’ and ‘resistance to aggression’ serve the same purpose of proclaiming an identity of interest between the dominant group and the world as a whole in the maintenance of peace. Moreover, as in the examples we have just considered, so long as the supremacy of the dominant group is sufficiently great, there is a sense in which this identity of interest exists. ‘England’, wrote a German professor in the nineteen-twenties, ‘is a solitary Power with a national programme which, while egotistic through and through, at the same time promises to the world something which the world passionately desires: order, progress and eternal peace.’53 When Mr Churchill declared that ‘the fortunes of the British Empire and its glory are inseparably interwoven with the fortunes of the world’,54 this statement had precisely the same foundation in fact as the statement that the prosperity of British manufacturers in the nineteenth century was inseparably interwoven with British prosperity as a whole. Moreover, the purpose of the statements was precisely the same, namely to establish the principle that the defence of the British Empire, or the prosperity of the British manufacturer, was a matter of common interest to the whole community, and that anyone who attacked it was therefore either immoral or muddle-headed. It is a familiar tactic of the privileged to throw moral discredit on the underprivileged by depicting them as disturbers of the peace; and this tactic is as readily applied internationally as within the national community. ‘International law and order’, writes Professor Toynbee of a recent crisis, ‘were in the true interests of the whole of mankind . . . whereas the desire to perpetuate the region of violence in international affairs was an anti-social desire which was not even in the ultimate interests of the citizens of the handful of states that officially professed this benighted and anachronistic creed.’55 This is precisely the argument, compounded of platitude and falsehood in about equal parts, which did duty in every strike in the early days of the British and American Labour movements. It was common form for employers, supported by the whole capitalist press, to denounce the ‘anti-social’ attitude of trade union leaders, to accuse them of attacking law and order and of introducing ‘the reign of violence’, and to declare that ‘true’ and ‘ultimate’ interests of the workers lay in peaceful co-operation with the employers.56 In the field of social relations, the disingenuous character of this argument has long been recognized. But just as the threat of class war by the proletarian is ‘a natural cynical reaction to the sentimental and dishonest efforts of the privileged classes to obscure the conflict of interest between classes by a constant emphasis on the minimum interests which they have in common’,57 so the warmongering of the dissatisfied Powers was the ‘natural, cynical reaction’ to the sentimental and dishonest platitudinizing of the satisfied Powers on the common interest in peace. When Hitler refused to believe ‘that God has permitted some nations first to acquire a world by force and then to defend this robbery with moralizing theories’,58 he was merely echoing in another context the Marxist denial of a community of interest between ‘haves’ and ‘have-nots’, the Marxist exposure of the interested character of ‘bourgeois morality’, and the Marxist demand for the expropriation of the expropriators.

The crisis of September 1938 demonstrated in a striking way the political implications of the assertion of a common interest in peace. When Briand proclaimed that ‘peace comes before all’, or Mr Eden that ‘there is no dispute which cannot be settled by peaceful means’,59 the assumption underlying these platitudes was that, so long as peace was maintained, no changes distasteful to France or Great Britain could be made in the status quo. In 1938, France and Great Britain were trapped by the slogans which they themselves had used in the past to discredit the dissatisfied Powers, and Germany had become sufficiently dominant (as France and Great Britain had hitherto been) to turn the desire for peace to her own advantage. About this time, a significant change occurred in the attitude of the German and Italian dictators. Hitler eagerly depicted Germany as a bulwark of peace menaced by warmongering democracies. The League of Nations, he declared in his Reichstag speech of 28 April 1939, is a ‘stirrer up of trouble’, and collective security means ‘continuous danger of war’. Mussolini borrowed the British formula about the possibility of settling all international disputes by peaceful means, and declared that ‘there are not in Europe at present problems so big and so active as to justify a war which from a European conflict would naturally become universal’.60 Such utterances were symptoms that Germany and Italy were already looking forward to the time when, as dominant Powers, they would acquire the vested interest in peace recently enjoyed by Great Britain and France, and be able to get their way by pillorying the democratic countries as enemies of peace. These developments may have made it easier to appreciate Halévy’s subtle observation that ‘propaganda against war is itself a form of war propaganda’.61

The realist critique of internationalism

The concept of internationalism is a special form of the doctrine of the harmony of interests. It yields to the same analysis; and there are the same difficulties about regarding it as an absolute standard independent of the interests and policies of those who promulgate it. ‘Cosmopolitanism’, wrote Sun Yat-sen, ‘is the same thing as China’s theory of world empire two thousand years ago . . . China once wanted to be sovereign lord of the earth and to stand above every other nation, so she espoused cosmopolitanism.’62 In the Egypt of the Eighteenth Dynasty, according to Freud, ‘imperialism was reflected in religion as universality and monotheism’.63 The doctrine of a single world-state, propagated by the Roman Empire and later by the Catholic Church, was the symbol of a claim to universal dominion. Modern internationalism has its genesis in seventeenth- and eighteenth-century France, during which French hegemony in Europe was at its height. This was the period which produced Sully’s Grand Dessin and the Abbé Saint-Pierre’s Projet de Paix Perpétuelle (both plans to perpetuate an international status quo favourable to the French monarchy), which saw the birth of the humanitarian and cosmopolitan doctrines of the Enlightenment, and which established French as the universal language of educated people. In the next century, the leadership passed to Great Britain, which became the home of internationalism. On the eve of the Great Exhibition of 1851 which, more than any other single event, established Great Britain’s title to world supremacy, the Prince Consort spoke movingly of ‘that great end to which . . . all history points – the realisation of the unity of mankind’;64 and Tennyson hymned ‘the parliament of man, the federation of the world’. France chose the moment of her greatest supremacy in the nineteen-twenties to launch a plan of ‘European Union’; and Japan shortly afterwards developed an ambition to proclaim herself the leader of a united Asia. It was symptomatic of the growing international predominance of the United States when widespread popularity was enjoyed in the late nineteen-thirties by the book of an American journalist advocating a world union of democracies, in which the United States would play the predominant role.65

Just as pleas for ‘national solidarity’ in domestic politics always come from a dominant group which can use this solidarity to strengthen its own control over the nation as a whole, so pleas for international solidarity and world union come from those dominant nations which may hope to exercise control over a unified world. Countries which are struggling to force their way into the dominant group naturally tend to invoke nationalism against the internationalism of the controlling Powers. In the sixteenth century, England opposed her nascent nationalism to the internationalism of the Papacy and the Empire. In the past century and a half Germany opposed her nascent nationalism to the internationalism first of France, then of Great Britain. This circumstance made her impervious to those universalist and humanitarian doctrines which were popular in eighteenth-century France and nineteenth-century Britain; and her hostility to internationalism was further aggravated after 1919, when Great Britain and France endeavoured to create a new ‘international order’ as a bulwark of their own predominance. ‘By “international”,’ wrote a German correspondent in The Times, ‘we have come to understand a conception that places other nations at an advantage over our own.’66 Nevertheless, there was little doubt that Germany, if she became supreme in Europe, would adopt international slogans and establish some kind of international organization to bolster up her power. A British Labour ex-Minister at one moment advocated the suppression of Article 16 of the Covenant of the League of Nations on the unexpected ground that the totalitarian states might some day capture the League and invoke that article to justify the use of force by themselves.67 It seemed more likely that they would seek to develop the Anti-Comintern Pact into some form of international organization. ‘The Anti-Comintern Pact’, said Hitler in the Reichstag on 30 January 1939, ‘will perhaps one day become the crystallization point of a group of Powers whose ultimate aim is none other than to eliminate the menace to the peace and culture of the world instigated by a satanic apparition.’ ‘Either Europe must achieve solidarity,’ remarked an Italian journal about the same time, ‘or the “axis” will impose it.’68 ‘Europe in its entirety’, said Goebbels, ‘is adopting a new order and a new orientation under the intellectual leadership of National Socialist Germany and Fascist Italy.’69 These were symptoms not of a change of heart, but of the fact that Germany and Italy felt themselves to be approaching the time when they might become strong enough to espouse internationalism. ‘International order’ and ‘international solidarity’ will always be slogans of those who feel strong enough to impose them on others.

The exposure of the real basis of the professedly abstract principles commonly invoked in international politics is the most damning and most convincing part of the realist indictment of utopianism. The nature of the charge is frequently misunderstood by those who seek to refute it. The charge is not that human beings fail to live up to their principles. It matters little that Wilson, who thought that the right was more precious than peace, and Briand, who thought that peace came even before justice, and Mr Eden, who believed in collective security, failed themselves, or failed to induce their countrymen, to apply these principles consistently. What matters is that these supposedly absolute and universal principles were not principles at all, but the unconscious reflexions of national policy based on a particular interpretation of national interest at a particular time. There is a sense in which peace and co-operation between nations or classes or individuals is a common and universal end irrespective of conflicting interests and politics. There is a sense in which a common interest exists in the maintenance of order, whether it be international order or ‘law and order’ within the nation. But as soon as the attempt is made to apply these supposedly abstract principles to a concrete political situation, they are revealed as the transparent disguises of selfish vested interests. The bankruptcy of utopianism resides not in its failure to live up to its principles, but in the exposure of its inability to provide any absolute and disinterested standard for the conduct of international affairs. The utopian, faced by the collapse of standards whose interested character he has failed to penetrate, takes refuge in condemnation of a reality which refuses to conform to these standards. A passage penned by the German historian Meinecke after the first world war is the best judgement by anticipation of the role of utopianism in the international politics of the period:

The profound defect of the Western, natural-law type of thought was that, when applied to the real life of the state, it remained a dead letter, did not penetrate the consciousness of statesmen, did not hinder the modern hypertrophy of state interest, and so led either to aimless complaints and doctrinaire suppositions or else to inner falsehood and cant.70

These ‘aimless complaints’, these ‘doctrinaire suppositions’, this ‘inner falsehood and cant’ will be familiar to all those who have studied what was written about international politics in English-speaking countries between the two world wars.

Notes

1.

|   |

Machiavelli, The Prince, chs. 15 and 23 (Engl. transl., Everyman’s Library, pp. 121, 193).

2.

|   |

Two curious recent illustrations may be cited. In the chapter of the Survey of International Affairs dealing with the Nazi revolution, Professor Toynbee declares that National Socialism is the ‘fulfilment of ideals . . . formulated . . . by Machiavelli’; and he reiterates this view in two further passages of considerable length in the same chapter (Survey of International Affairs, 1934, pp. 111, 117–19, 126–8). In the trial of Zinoviev, Kamenev and others in Moscow in August 1936, the Public Prosecutor, Vyshinsky, quoted a passage from Kamenev’s writings in which Machiavelli had been praised as ‘a master of political aphorism and a brilliant dialectician’, and accused Kamenev of having ‘adopted the rules of Machiavelli’ and ‘developed them to the utmost point of unscrupulousness and immorality’ (The Case of the Trotskyite-Zinovievite Centre, pp. 138–9).

3.

|   |

Bacon, On the Advancement of Learning, vii. ch. 2.

4.

|   |

Hobbes’s scheme, ‘there was in theory no place for any new force or principle beyond the laws of motion found at the beginning; there were merely complex cases of mechanical causation’ (Sabine, History of Political Thought, p. 458).

5.

|   |

Introduction to A Defence of Liberty against Tyrants (Vindiciae contra Tyrannos), ed. Laski, p. 45.

6.

|   |

Hobbes, Leviathan, ch. xv.

7.

|   |

Spinoza, Tractatus Politicus, i. pp. 2–3.

8.

|   |

Ibid., Introduction.

9.

|   |

The concluding words of Buckle’s History of Civilisation.

10.

|   |

Kjellen, Der Staat als Lebensform, p. 81. Compare the opening words of Crowe’s famous memorandum on British foreign policy: ‘The general character of England’s foreign policy is determined by the immutable conditions of her geographical situation’ (British Documents on the Origin of the War, ed. Gooch and Temperley, iii. p. 397).

11.

|   |

International Conciliation, No. 194, January 1924, p. 3.

12.

|   |

Marx, Capital, Preface to Ist ed. (Engl. transl., Everyman’s Library, p. 863).

13.

|   |

Lenin, Works (2nd Russian ed.) x. p. 207.

14.

|   |

Ibid., xxii, p. 194.

15.

|   |

Croce, Storia della storiografia italiana, i. p. 26.

16.

|   |

Hegel, Philosophie der Weltgeschichte (Lasson’s ed.), p. 55.

17.

|   |

Conciliation Internationale, No. 5–6, 1937, p. 520.

18.

|   |

Lukacs, Geschichte und Klassenhewusstsein, p. 215.

19.

|   |

Proceedings of the Aristotelian Society, 1915–16, p. 302.

20.

|   |

Burnet, Essay upon Government, p. 10.

21.

|   |

Dicey, Law and Opinion (1905 ed.), p. 27.

22.

|   |

J. A. Hobson, Free Thought in the Social Sciences, p. 190.

23.

|   |

Hale’vy, The Growth of Philosophic Radicalism (Engl. transl.), p. 104.

24.

|   |

M. Dobb, Political Economy and Capitalism, p. 188.

25.

|   |

L. T. Hobhouse, The Unity of Western Civilisation, ed. F. S. Marvin (3rd ed.), pp. 177–8.

26.

|   |

Bertrand Russell, Which Way Peace?, p. 158.

27.

|   |

Acton, History of Freedom, p. 62.

28.

|   |

Carl Becker, Yale Review, xxvii, p. 461.

29.

|   |

League of Nations: Official Journal, November 1935, p. 1140.

30.

|   |

British Documents on the Origins of the War, ed. Gooch and Temperley, vi. p. 131.

31.

|   |

House of Commons, 14 March 1938: Official Report, cols. 95–9.

32.

|   |

The Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: War and Peace, ed. R. S. Baker, i. p. 16.

33.

|   |

League of Nations: Ninth Assembly, p. 83.

34.

|   |

R.S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson and World Settlement, iii, p. 120. There is an amusing nineteenth-century parallel. ‘Privateering’, wrote Queen Victoria at the time of the Conference of Paris in 1856, ‘is a kind of Piracy which disgraces our civilisation; its abolition throughout the whole world would be a great step in advance.’ We are not surprised to read that ‘the privateer was then, like the submarine in modern times, the weapon of the weaker naval Power’ (Sir William Malkin, British Year Book of International Law, viii. pp. 6, 30).

35.

|   |

Published as League of Nations Union Pamphlet No. 76, p. 8. The very word ‘militarism’ conveys to most English readers the same connotation of the peculiar wickedness of armies. It was left to an American historian, Dr W. L. Langer, to coin the counterpart ‘navalism’, which has won significantly little acceptance.

36.

|   |

Dicey, Law and Opinion in England (2nd ed.), pp. 14–15.

37.

|   |

The Times, 27 August 1885.

38.

|   |

Maurice and Arthur, The Life of Lord Wolseley, p. 314.

39.

|   |

W. T. Stead, The Last Will and Testament of Cecil J. Rhodes, p. 58.

40.

|   |

Review of Reviews, 15 January 1891.

41.

|   |

Spencer Wilkinson, Government and the War, p. 116.

42.

|   |

Quoted in Beard, The Rise of American Civilisation, ii. p. 646.

43.

|   |

Quoted in Manchester Guardian, 18 October 1935.

44.

|   |

Toynbee, Survey of International Affairs, 1935, ii. p. 46.

45.

|   |

Headway, November 1937.

46.

|   |

Carl Becker, Yale Review, xxvii. p. 452.

47.

|   |

Count Sforza, Foreign Affairs, October 1927, p. 67.

48.

|   |

Quoted in H. F. Pringle, Theodore Roosevelt, p. 318.

49.

|   |

Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: The New Democracy, ed. R. S. Baker, i. p. 104.

50.

|   |

Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: The New Democracy, ed. R. S. Baker, i. pp. 318–19.

51.

|   |

Ibid., ii. p. 414.

52.

|   |

Quoted in Toynbee, Survey of International Affairs, 1936, p. 319.

53.

|   |

Dibelius, England, p. 109.

54.

|   |

Winston Churchill, Arms and the Covenant, p. 272.

55.

|   |

Toynbee, Survey of International Affair, 1935, ii. p. 46.

56.

|   |

‘Pray earnestly that right may triumph’, said the representative of the Philadelphia coal-owners in an early strike organised by the United Mine Workers, ‘remembering that the Lord God Omnipotent still reigns, and that His reign is one of law and order, and not of violence and crime’ (H. F. Pringle, Theodore Roosevelt, p. 267).

57.

|   |

R. Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, p. 153.

58.

|   |

Speech in the Reichstag, 30 January 1939.

59.

|   |

League of Nations: Eighteenth Assembly, p. 63.

60.

|   |

The Times, 15 May 1939.

61.

|   |

Halévy, A History of the English People in 1895–1905 (Engl. transl.), i. Introduction, p. xi.

62.

|   |

Sun Yat-sen, San Min Chu I (Engl. transl.), pp. 68–9.

63.

|   |

Sigmund Freud, Moses and Monotheism, p. 36.

64.

|   |

T. Martin, Life of the Prince Consort, iii. p. 247.

65.

|   |

Clarence Streit, Union Now.

66.

|   |

The Times, 5 November 1938.

67.

|   |

Lord Marley in the House of Lords, 30 November 1938: Official Report, col. 228.

68.

|   |

Relazioni Internazionali, quoted in The Times, 5 December 1938.

69.

|   |

Völkischer Beobachter, 1 April 1939.

70.

|   |

Meinecke, Staatsra son, p. 533.

CHAPTER ELEVEN

The Sanctity of Treaties

One of the functions of law necessary to civilized life is to protect rights which have been created by private contracts concluded in a manner recognized by the law as valid. International law upholds, with some reservations, rights created by international treaties and agreements. This principle is essential to the existence of any kind of international community and is, as we have seen, recognized in theory by all states. The fact that the only written obligations of states are those contained in treaties, and that customary international law is limited in scope and sometimes uncertain in content, has given to treaties a more prominent place in international law than is occupied by contracts in municipal law. Indeed the contents of treaties are sometimes misleadingly spoken of as if they were a part of international law itself, though nobody would regard the provisions of a contract between Smith and Robinson as a part of municipal law. The principle of the sanctity of treaties has thus been thrown into undue relief, which was further intensified by the controversy over the peace treaties of 1919–20. Between the two wars writers, especially those from countries interested in the maintenance of the peace settlement, attempted to treat the rule pacta sunt servanda not merely as a fundamental rule of international law, but as the cornerstone of international society – an attitude mockingly described by a German writer as ‘pacta-sunt-servanda-ism’.1 The issue has become one of the most contentious in the whole field of international politics; and confusion has often been caused by failure to distinguish between ‘the sanctity of treaties’ as a rule of international law and ‘the sanctity of treaties’ as a principle of international ethics.

The legal and moral validity of treaties

In spite of the universal recognition by all countries that treaties are in principle legally binding, international law before 1914 was reluctant to treat as absolute the binding character of treaty obligations. Account had to be taken of the fact that, while states interested in maintenance of the status quo vigorously asserted the unconditional validity of treaties in international law, a state whose interests were adversely affected by a treaty commonly repudiated it as soon as it could do so with impunity. France in 1848 announced that ‘the treaties of 1815 are no longer valid in the eyes of the French Republic’.2 Russia in 1871 repudiated the Straits Convention placing restrictions on the passage of her warships which had been imposed on her at the conclusion of the Crimean War. These were merely the most conspicuous of several similar nineteenth-century occurrences. To meet such conditions, international lawyers evolved the doctrine that a so-called clausula rebus sic stantibus was implicit in every treaty, i.e. that the obligations of a treaty were binding in international law so long as the conditions prevailing at the time of the conclusion of the treaty continued, and no longer. This doctrine, if carried to its logical conclusion, would appear to lead to the position that a treaty had no authority other than the power relationship of the parties to it, and that when this relationship alters the treaty lapses. This position was not infrequently adopted. ‘Every treaty’, wrote Bismarck in a famous phrase, ‘has the significance only of a constatation of a definite position in European affairs. The reserve rebus sic stantibus is always silently understood.’3 The same effect is produced by the doctrine occasionally propounded that a state enjoys the unconditional right to denounce any treaty at any time. This view was stated in its most uncompromising form by Theodore Roosevelt: ‘The nation has as a matter of course a right to abrogate a treaty in a solemn and official manner for what she regards as a sufficient cause, just exactly as she has a right to declare war or exercise another power for a sufficient cause.’4 Woodrow Wilson observed in private conversation during the Peace Conference that, when he was a teacher of international law, he had always supposed that a state had the power to denounce any treaty by which it was bound at any time.5 In 1915, a distinguished neutral international lawyer of the ‘naturalist’ school wrote of the rule pacta sunt servanda that ‘nobody regards it as a rule of law which is valid without exception either within or without the state’.6

Even Great Britain which, as the strongest Power in the world, had most interest in upholding the validity of treaties, was manifestly disinclined to accept the view that treaty obligations were unconditionally binding. The most famous example is that of the Belgian Guarantee Treaty of 1839, under which the principal European Powers, including Great Britain, bound themselves jointly and severally to resist any violation of the neutrality of Belgium by one of their number. In 1870 Gladstone told the House of Commons, in a passage which was cited with approval by Grey in his speech of 3 August 1914, that he was ‘not able to subscribe to the doctrine of those who have held in this House what plainly amounts to an assertion that the simple fact of the existence of the guarantee is binding on every party of it, irrespective altogether of the particular position in which it may find itself at the time that the occasion for acting on the guarantee arises’. Such an interpretation Gladstone thought ‘rigid’ and ‘impracticable’.7 A confidential minute written in 1908 by Lord Hardinge, then Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, was conceived in the same spirit:

The liability undoubtedly exists . . . but whether we could be called on to carry out our obligation and to vindicate the neutrality of Belgium in opposing its violation must necessarily depend upon our policy at the time and the circumstances of the moment. Supposing that France violated the neutrality of Belgium in a war against Germany it is, under present circumstances, doubtful whether England or Russia would move a finger to maintain Belgian neutrality, while, if the neutrality of Belgium were violated by Germany, it is probable that the converse would be the case.

Grey, commenting in a further minute, merely observed that this reflexion was ‘to the point’.8

Another principle not less elastic than the clausula has sometimes been invoked to justify non-fulfilment of international obligations – the principle of ‘necessity’ or ‘vital interests’. It is a well-known legal maxim that nobody can be called on to perform the impossible; and the impossible is sometimes held in international law to include acts detrimental to the vital interests (meaning primarily the security) of the state. Some writers have specifically held that every state has a legal right of self-preservation which overrides any obligation to other states. This view is likely to carry particular weight in time of war. In its note of protest against British blockade measures in December 1914, the United States Government laid it down as the principle of international law that belligerents should not interfere with neutral commerce ‘unless such interference is manifestly an imperative necessity to protect their national safety, and then only to the extent that it is a necessity’. The British Government gratefully accepted this interpretation, and was thenceforth able to justify its blockade activities on the uncontested ground of an ‘imperative necessity’ whose requirements nobody was as well qualified as itself to assess.9 In such emergencies, the layman is apt to discard legal niceties and arrive at the same result by other methods. At the time of the Jameson Raid, The Times published a poem by the Poet Laureate which opened with these disarming lines:

Let lawyers and statesmen addle

Their pates over points of law:

If sound be our sword and saddle

And gun-gear, who cares one straw?10

‘Damn the law, I want the Canal built,’ was a saying popularly attributed to Theodore Roosevelt at the time of the Panama crisis. In 1939 a Japanese ‘naval spokesman’, commenting on the boarding of foreign vessels in Chinese waters by Japanese patrols, is reported to have said: ‘It is not a question of having the right to do this. It is something which is necessary and we are doing it.’11 ‘Once it [i.e. the nation] is in danger of oppression or annihilation,’ wrote Hitler, ‘the question of legality plays a subordinate role.’12

Indeed, where justification is explicitly or implicitly offered for the nonfulfilment of treaty obligations, it is often difficult to discover from the words used whether the alleged justification is based on legal or on moral grounds. Is the view taken that, by the operation of clausula rebus sic stantibus or for some other reason, the obligation is no longer binding in law? Or is the legal obligation admitted, and is it argued that the state is entitled to disregard the law on the ground that it is immoral, unreasonable or impracticable, just as the citizen is sometimes morally entitled to disregard the national law? Broadly speaking, it may be said that prior to 1914 the rule pacta sunt servanda was elastically interpreted and the nonfulfilment of obligations was apt to be defended as legally admissible, whereas since 1919 the interpretation of the rule has tended to become more rigid, and nonfulfilment has been defended mainly on the ground that considerations of reason or morality entitled the state to disregard its strictly legal obligation. The dilemma of international law is that of ecclesiastical dogma. Elastic interpretation adapted to diverse needs increases the number of the faithful. Rigid interpretation, though theoretically desirable, provokes secessions from the church. It cannot be doubted that the more frequent and open repudiation of the rules of international law since 1919 has been due in part to the well-intentioned efforts of the victorious Powers to strengthen those rules and to interpret them with greater rigidity and precision.

An examination of the numerous breaches of treaty obligations during this period yields less definite results than might have been expected; for the state concerned in many cases defended itself either by denying that any breach of treaty obligations has occurred, or by alleging that the treaty had in the first instance been violated by the other party. In December 1932, the French Chamber of Deputies refused to carry out the French War debt agreement with the United States on the ground that ‘the determining circumstances’ had changed since the conclusion of the agreement six years earlier – the nearest approach since 1919 to an explicit invocation of the clausula rebus sic stantibus.13 The British default on the Anglo-American War debt agreement was justified on the ground of ‘economic necessity’. But the main ground of the argument was not legal, but moral: the burden imposed by the agreement was ‘unreasonable’ and ‘inequitable’.14 The Times took the view that the debt ‘had not the same moral validity as an ordinary commercial transaction’.15 At an earlier stage, Neville Chamberlain, then Chancellor of the Exchequer, had explicitly admitted that the obligation was legally binding, but had appealed to other obligations which might be rated higher than those of law:

When we are told that contracts must be kept sacred, and that we must on no account depart from the obligations which we have undertaken, it must not be forgotten that we have other obligations and responsibilities, obligations not only to our countrymen, but to many millions of human beings throughout the world, whose happiness or misery may depend upon how far the fulfilment of these obligations is insisted upon on the one side and met on the other.16

In repudiating the military clauses of the Versailles Treaty in March 1935, Germany based her action on the alleged failure of the other parties to the treaty to implement their own obligations to disarm. A year later, the repudiation of the Locarno Treaty was justified on the ground that, through the action of France in concluding the Franco-Soviet Pact, the treaty had ‘ceased in practice to exist’.17 These were at any rate ostensibly legal arguments. But in a public speech shortly after the occupation of the Rhineland, Hitler rejected the legal in favour of the moral plea: ‘If the rest of the world clings to the letter of treaties, I cling to an eternal morality.’18

On the whole, therefore, it may be said that breaches of treaties between the two wars were excused, not on the legal ground of derogations admitted by international law to the principle of the sanctity of treaties, but on the ethical ground that certain treaties, though legally binding, lack moral validity. It was not denied that breaches of such treaties are technical breaches of international law; but they were an offence against international morality. It is important for the student of international ethics and international law to study the qualities which were popularly supposed to make treaties morally disreputable and therefore morally invalid.

Treaties signed under duress

In the first place, it came to be felt that there was a moral taint about treaties signed under duress. This feeling attached itself mainly to the Versailles Treaty, signed by Germany under the duress of a five-day ultimatum. German propaganda worked hard to popularize the conception of the Versailles Treaty as a Diktat which had no moral validity; and the idea enjoyed widespread currency after the conclusion of the Locarno Treaty, when British and French statesmen rashly vied with Stresemann in emphasizing the moral significance of the voluntary acceptance by Germany of some of the obligations accepted under duress at Versailles. The attitude adopted to treaties concluded under duress is dependent on the attitude adopted to war; for every treaty which brings a war to an end is almost inevitably accepted by the loser under duress. So long therefore as any kind of war whatever is recognized as moral, treaties concluded under duress cannot be unconditionally condemned as immoral. The moral objections most frequently expressed against the Versailles Treaty seem, in fact, to have been based not so much on its signature under duress as on the severity of its contents, and on the fact that the Allied Governments, reversing the procedure followed at all important peace conferences down to and including that of Brest-Litovsk, refused to engage in oral negotiations with the plenipotentiaries of the defeated Power. This act of unwisdom probably discredited the treaty more than the ultimatum which preceded its signature.

Inequitable treaties

Secondly, the view was commonly taken that treaties may be morally invalidated by the character of their contents. There cannot indeed be any rule of international law corresponding to the rule of municipal law voiding contracts which are ‘immoral’ or ‘contrary to public policy’. The absence of an international political order makes impossible any legal definition of international public policy or of what is internationally immoral.19 But those who regard the contents of a given international treaty as immoral will, generally speaking, concede to the injured state the moral right to repudiate it; for international law provides no other means of redress. It should, moreover, be observed that there is a tendency to concede the same moral right to repudiate a treaty which is not, properly speaking, immoral, but which is inequitable in the sense that it imposes conditions flagrantly incompatible with the existing relations of power between the contracting parties. The disarmament clauses of the Versailles Treaty were widely regarded as lacking in validity because it was unreasonable to impose a position of permanent inferiority on a Great Power. In general, the reproach was levelled against the Versailles Treaty that it sought to perpetuate the temporary weakness of Germany due to her collapse at the end of the War. This argument is not perhaps strictly ethical, since it is rooted in the power position and recognizes a moral right based simply on strength. But it is an illustration of the curious way in which power and ethics are intertwined in all political problems. A somewhat similar case arose in connexion with Article 16 of the Covenant of the League of Nations. When the United States failed to ratify the Covenant, it was widely felt that the obligations imposed by that Article were no longer morally binding, since members of the League could not reasonably be expected to take measures which might bring on them the enmity of so powerful a country. The test of what is commonly recognized as reasonable applies to the moral validity of treaties as to other problems of international morality.

Treaties as instruments of power

The third consideration which is sometimes invoked to deny the morally binding character of international treaties is of a more sweeping kind. It is designed to cast doubts on the moral credit not of particular treaties, but of all treaties as being by their nature instruments of power and therefore devoid of moral value. A Marxist writer has argued that, in capitalist society, the legal enforcement of contracts is merely a method of using the power of the state to protect and further the interests of the ruling class.20 In the same way, it can be maintained with considerable show of reason that insistence on the legal validity of international treaties is a weapon used by the ruling nations to maintain their supremacy over weaker nations on whom the treaties have been imposed. Such an argument is implicit in the realist view of law as an oppressive instrument of power divorced from ethics.

The argument is assisted by the elastic and inconsistent manner in which the doctrine of the sanctity of treaties has been applied in the practice of states. In 1932–33, the French and British Governments were insisting with particular vehemence that the disarmament clauses of the Versailles Treaty were legally binding on Germany, and could be revised only with the consent of the interested Powers. In December 1932, the French Chamber of Deputies found reasons for refusing to carry out the French war debt agreement with the United States. In June 1933, the British Government ceased to pay the regular instalments due under its war debt agreement, substituting minor ‘token payments’; and a year later these token payments came to an end. Yet in 1935 Great Britain and France once more joined in a solemn condemnation of Germany for unilaterally repudiating her obligations under the disarmament clauses of the Versailles Treaty. Such inconsistencies are so common that the realist finds little difficulty in reducing them to a simple rule. The element of power is inherent in every political treaty. The contents of such a treaty reflect in some degree the relative strength of the contracting parties. Stronger states will insist on the sanctity of the treaties concluded by them with weaker states. Weaker states will renounce treaties concluded by them with stronger states as soon as the power position alters and the weaker state feels itself strong enough to reject or modify the obligation. Since 1918, the United States have concluded no treaty with a stronger state, and have therefore unreservedly upheld the sanctity of treaties. Great Britain concluded the war debt agreement with a country financially stronger than herself, and defaulted. She concluded no other important treaty with a stronger Power and, with this single exception, upheld the sanctity of treaties. The countries which had concluded the largest number of treaties with states stronger than themselves, and subsequently strengthened their position, were Germany, Italy and Japan; and these are the countries which renounced or violated the largest number of treaties. But it would be rash to assume any moral distinction between these different attitudes. There is no reason to assume that these countries would insist any less strongly than Great Britain or the United States on the sanctity of treaties favourable to themselves concluded by them with weaker states.

The case is convincing as far as it goes. The rule pacta sunt servanda is not a moral principle, and its application cannot always be justified on ethical grounds. It is a rule of international law; and as such it not only is, but is universally recognized to be, necessary to the existence of an international society. But law does not purport to solve every political problem; and where it fails, the fault often lies with those who seek to put it to uses for which it was never intended. It is no reproach to law to describe it as a bulwark of the existing order. The essence of law is to promote stability and maintain the existing framework of society; and it is perfectly natural everywhere for conservatives to describe themselves as the party of law and order, and to denounce radicals as disturbers of the peace and enemies of the law. The history of every society reveals a strong tendency on the part of those who want important changes in the existing order to commit acts which are illegal or which can plausibly be denounced as such by conservatives. It is true that in highly organized societies, where legally constituted machinery exists for bringing about changes in the law, this tendency to illegal action is mitigated. But it is never removed altogether. Radicals are always more likely than conservatives to come into conflict with the law.

Before 1914, international law did not condemn as illegal resort to war for the purpose of changing the existing international order; and no legally constituted machinery existed for bringing about changes in any other way. After 1918 opinion condemning ‘aggressive’ war became almost universal, and nearly all the nations of the world signed a pact renouncing resort to war as an instrument of policy. While therefore resort to war for the purpose of altering the status quo now usually involves the breach of a treaty obligation and is accordingly illegal in international law, no effective international machinery has been constituted for bringing about changes by pacific means. The rude nineteenth-century system, or lack of system, was logical in recognizing as legal the one effective method of changing the status quo. The rejection of the traditional method as illegal and the failure to provide any effective alternative have made contemporary international law a bulwark of the existing order to an extent unknown in previous international law or in the municipal law of any civilized country. This is the most fundamental cause of the recent decline of respect for international law; and those who, in deploring the phenomenon, fail to recognize its origin, not unnaturally expose themselves to the charge of hypocrisy or of obtuseness.

Of all the considerations which render unlikely the general observance of the legal rule of the sanctity of treaties, and which provide a plausible moral justification for the repudiation of treaties, this last is by far the most important. Respect for international law and for the sanctity of treaties will not be increased by the sermons of those who, having most to gain from the maintenance of the existing order, insist most firmly on the morally binding character of the law. Respect for law and treaties will be maintained only in so far as the law recognizes effective political machinery through which it can itself be modified and superseded. There must be a clear recognition of that play of political forces which is antecedent to all law. Only when these forces are in stable equilibrium can the law perform its social function without becoming a tool in the hands of the defenders of the status quo. The achievement of this equilibrium is not a legal, but a political task.

Notes

1.

|    |

Walz in Deutsches Recht, Jg. IV. (1934), p. 525. Professor Lauterpacht’s remark that the rule pacta sunt servanda ‘constitutes the highest, irreducible, final criterion’ in international society (The Function of Law in the International Community, p. 418) is a good example of the attitude criticized.

2.

|    |

Lamartine’s Circular of 5 March 1848, published in the Moniteur of that date.

3.

|    |

Bismarck, Gedanken und Erinnerungen, ii. p. 258.

4.

|    |

Quoted in H. F. Pringle, Theodore Roosevelt, p. 309.

5.

|    |

Miller, The Drafting of the Covenant, i. p. 293.

6.

|    |

Krabbe, The Modern Idea of the State (Engl. transl.), p. 266.

7.

|    |

Quoted in Grey, Speeches on Foreign Affairs, 1904–1914, p. 307.

8.

|    |

British Documents on the Origin of the War, ed. Gooch and Temperley, viii. pp. 377–8.

9.

|    |

The correspondence was published in Cmd 7816 of 1915.

10.

|    |

The Times, 11 January 1896.

11.

|    |

The Times, 26 May 1939.

12.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 104.

13.

|    |

Resolution of 14 December 1932, in Documents on International Affairs, 1932,

14.

|    |

The quotations are from the British note of 4 June 1934 (Cmd 4609).

15.

|    |

The Times, 2 June 1934.

16.

|    |

Speech in the House of Commons, 14 December 1932, in Documents on International Affairs, 1932, p. 128.

17.

|    |

Diplomatic Discussions Directed Towards a European Settlement, Cmd 5143, p. 78.

18.

|    |

Quoted in Toynbee, Survey of International Affairs, 1936, p. 319. Such pleas are not peculiarly modern and have often been regarded as legitimate. As recently as 1908, a distinguished English historian used of Pitt words which, with the bare change of proper names, are precisely apposite to Hitler’s attitude: ‘His support of the British claim as “from God and Nature” to override the artificial restrictions of unjust treaties, his denunciation of the Convention of the Pardo as “a stipulation for the national ignominy”, voiced the inarticulate sentiment of the new England’ (Quarterly Review, October 1908, p. 325). A later passage in the same article runs as follows: ‘By the alchemy of his own intense vision and political ideals, he imposed on England a conception of national development and national ends based on an ideal of Imperialist expansion to realize which the nation must sacrifice everything or cease to believe in its own right and power to exist’ (ibid., pp. 334–5). It is interesting to observe that the writer clearly regarded these phrases as eulogistic.

19.

|    |

Some German writers after 1919 tried to maintain that treaties are invalid in international law if they conflict with the ‘natural law of nations’. The literature is reviewed by Verdross, American Journal of International Law, xxxi. (October 1937), pp. 571 sqq. But this view has found little support elsewhere. On the occasion of a judgement by the Permanent Court of International Justice in 1934, the German judge, in an individual opinion, expressed the view that the Court ‘would never apply a convention whose contents were contrary to bonnes ma:urs’ (Permanent Court of International Justice, Series A/B No. 63, p. 150). But the Court as such never appears to have committed itself to this proposition.

20.

|    |

Renner, Die Rechtsinstitute des Privatrechts und ibre soziale Funktion, p. 55.

CHAPTER TWELVE

The Judicial Settlement of International Disputes

Besides upholding legal rights, the law provides machinery for settling disputes about these rights. The jurisdiction of national courts is compulsory. Any person cited before a court must enter an appearance or lose his case by default; and the decision of the court is binding on all concerned.

International law, though it provides machinery for the settlement of disputes, recognizes no compulsory jurisdiction. Down to the end of the nineteenth century, the judicial process as applied to international disputes almost invariably took the form of an ad hoc agreement to submit a particular dispute to an arbitrator or arbitrators, whose method of appointment was fixed by the agreement and whose verdict was accepted in advance as binding. Under the Hague Convention of 1899, a Permanent Court of Arbitration was established at The Hague. This was, however, not a court, but a standing panel from which suitable arbitrators could be selected by states desiring to resort to arbitration. The Permanent Court of International Justice established under the Covenant of the League of Nations really was a court sitting as such. But it exercised jurisdiction only with the consent of the parties, whether that consent was expressed in an ad hoc agreement relating to the particular dispute or in a general agreement between the parties to submit to the Court all disputes falling within certain categories. ‘It is well established in international law’, declared the Court itself in one of its judgements, ‘that no state can, without its consent, be compelled to submit its disputes with other states either to mediation or to arbitration or to any other kind of pacific settlement.’1

Justiciable and non-justiciable disputes

In municipal law, all disputes are theoretically justiciable; for if the point at issue is covered by no legal rule, the answer of the court will be that the complainant has no case. It is true that the complainant may not be satisfied with this answer, and may seek to obtain redress by political action. But this merely means that he does not want a legal answer, not that the law has no answer to give, or that the answer is not legally binding. In international law, all disputes are not justiciable; for no court is competent unless the parties to the dispute have agreed to confer jurisdiction on it and to recognize its decision as binding. Many treaties are in existence in which the parties define the kinds of disputes which they agree to recognize as justiciable as between themselves. In some treaties before 1914, disputes of certain limited and specific categories were recognized as justiciable. In others, the definition of justiciable disputes took a negative and somewhat elastic form: the parties to the treaty undertook to submit to arbitration any dispute between them which did not affect their ‘vital interests’, ‘independence’ or ‘national honour’. The nearest approach to a definition of justiciable disputes was contained in Article 13 of the League Covenant, and repeated in Article 36 of the Permanent Court, which enumerated various kinds of dispute ‘declared to be among those which are generally suitable for submission to arbitration or judicial settlement’. Finally several arbitration treaties concluded after 1919, notably those negotiated at Locarno, recognized as justiciable what were called disputes between the parties ‘as to their respective rights’.

The formulae of the Covenant and the Statute and of the Locarno arbitration treaties have given a strong impetus to the idea that international disputes could be classified by an objective test as ipso facto justiciable and ipso facto non-justiciable. Any such classification rests on an illusion. The formulae in question provide no objective definition of a justiciable dispute. They merely indicate certain kinds of dispute which the parties to these instruments agree to recognize as justiciable between themselves. The formula of the Covenant and the Statue is not really a definition at all, but an enumeration of examples which does not purport to be either exhaustive or (as the qualification ‘generally’ shows) authoritative.2 The Locarno formula is an attempt to give an objective character to the distinction between justiciable and non-justiciable disputes by identifying it with the distinction between conflicts of legal right and conflicts of interest. This formula has little practical value. It merely binds the parties to recognize as justiciable any dispute which they agree to regard as an issue of law. Either party can withdraw any dispute from arbitration by the simple process of placing itself on some other ground than that of legal right. Thus, the British Government, if it had been bound by such a treaty, would presumably have refused to submit to arbitration its default on the war debt agreement with the United States on the ground that the point at issue was not the legal right of the United States to demand payment, and that the dispute was not therefore one as to ‘respective rights’. As Professor Lauterpacht has conclusively shown, there is no objective criterion of the ‘suitability’ of a dispute for judicial settlement. ‘It is not the nature of an individual dispute which makes it unfit for judicial settlement but the unwillingness of a state to have it settled by the application of law.’3 The question which confronts us is twofold: Why are states willing to submit only certain kinds of dispute to judicial settlement, and why do they find it so difficult to define in clear terms what kinds of dispute they are willing to submit?

The answer to this question must be sought in the necessary relation of law to politics. The judicial settlement of disputes presupposes the existence of law and the recognition that it is binding; and the agreement which makes the law and which treats it as binding is a political fact. The applicability of judicial procedure depends therefore on explicit or implicit political agreement. In international relations, political agreement tends to be restricted to those spheres which do not affect the security and existence of the state; and it is primarily in these spheres that the judicial settlement of disputes is effective. The majority of international disputes which have in the past been settled by arbitration or by some other legal procedure have been either pecuniary claims or disputes about national frontiers in remote and sparsely inhabited regions. The exclusion, in arbitration treaties concluded before 1914, of disputes affecting ‘vital interests’, ‘independence’ or ‘national honour’ meant the exclusion of precisely those matters on which political agreement could not be attained. When political disagreement threatened, arbitration was recognized as impracticable. We shall see presently that what is virtually the same reservation was maintained in subsequent agreements for arbitration or judicial settlement in the form of the exclusion from these agreements of disputes endangering the sanctity of existing treaties or existing legal rights.

The same consideration explains why no definition of disputes recognized as justiciable can be universally or permanently valid; for political agreement is a factor which varies from place to place and from time to time.4 Prior to 1917 there was a general political understanding throughout the world that the property rights of individuals were valid, and that a foreigner whose property was for any reason confiscated by the government of the country in which it was situated had a claim in international law to compensation. So long as this understanding existed, claims based upon it could be settled by arbitration. With the establishment of the Soviet régime in Russia, this understanding ceased to apply to that country; and when the Soviet Government made its first important international appearance at the Genoa Conference in 1922, it was careful to scout in advance the idea that property claims against it should be submitted to arbitration. ‘In the trial of disputes of this kind’, ran the memorandum which it submitted to the Conference, ‘the specific disagreements will inevitably end in opposing to one another two forms of property.... In such circumstances there can be no question of an impartial super-arbiter.’ And when, at the subsequent Hague Conference, the British delegate pathetically enquired ‘whether it would be impossible to find a single impartial judge in the whole world’, Mr Litvinov firmly replied that ‘it was necessary to face the fact that there was not one world, but two, a Soviet world and a non-Soviet world’.5 ‘Impartiality’ is a meaningless concept where there is no common ground at all between the two contending views. Judicial procedure cannot operate without accepted political postulates.

The assumption of the British delegate just quoted that the obstacle to international arbitration was the difficulty of finding impartial judges had been heard on previous occasions. ‘The great obstacle to the extension of arbitration’, declared the American delegate at the Hague Conference of 1907, ‘is not the unwillingness of civilized nations to submit their disputes to the decision of an arbitral tribunal; it is rather an apprehension that the tribunal selected will not be impartial.’ Lord Salisbury is quoted in a similar sense.6 This opinion rests on a misapprehension. The potential personal bias of the international judge is not the real stumbling-block. The popular prejudice against submitting matters of national concern to the verdict of a ‘foreigner’ is based primarily, not on the belief that the foreign judge will be biased as between the parties, but on the fact that there are certain fundamentals of a political character which we are not prepared to have challenged by any foreign authority, whether judicial or political. The abolition of private ownership for Soviet Russia, the right of blockade for Great Britain, the Monroe Doctrine for the United States are familiar examples of such political fundamentals. Such fundamentals need not, however, be major issues at all. Palmerston treated the Don Pacifico episode in 1850, and Signor Mussolini the murder of an Italian general in Greece in 1923, as political issues which they were not prepared to submit to judicial settlement.7

But there is another and more general sense in which the absence of common political presupposition impedes the development of the judicial process in the international community. Municipal law, though far more fully and minutely developed than international law, is never wholly self-sufficing. The application of the law to the particular case is always liable to involve an element of judicial discretion, since the legislator can hardly have foreseen all the relevant circumstances of every case arising under the law. ‘There are many situations’, writes Dean Pound, ‘where the course of judicial action is left to be determined wholly by the judge’s individual sense of what is right.’8 It would perhaps have been fairer to say that the good judge will be guided in such cases not so much by his own ‘individual sense of what is right’ as by the sense of right generally accepted by the community whose servant he is. But that some ‘sense of what is right’, whether individual or general, is a necessary ingredient of many judicial decisions, few will care to deny. The importance of the political presuppositions which inspire the Supreme Court of the United States in the interpretation of the Constitution, and the way in which, in the course of American history, these presuppositions have changed in response to changing social conditions, is well known.9 The problem is, in its final analysis, the fundamental one of the relation of the rights of the individual to the needs of the community. Every national community has necessarily found a working solution of this problem. The international community has not yet done so. The controversy about the freedom of the seas shows that Great Britain would be unwilling to risk any interpretation of her maritime rights by an international court in the light of the supposed needs of the international community as a whole; and there are important matters on which every other Great Power would make similar reservations. The absence of an accepted view of the general good of the community as a whole overriding the particular good of any individual member of it, which we have already noted as the crucial problem of international morality, also stands in the way of the development of judicial settlement in its application to international disputes.

We find, therefore, in the problem of the justiciability of international disputes another illustration of the fact that law is a function of political society, is dependent for its development on the development of that society, and is conditioned by the political presuppositions which that society shares in common. It follows that the strengthening of international law, and the extension of the number and character of international disputes recognized as suitable for judicial settlement, is a political, not a legal, problem. There is no principle of law which enables one to decide that a given issue is suitable for treatment by legal methods. The decision is political; and its character is likely to be determined by the political development of the international community or of the political relations between the countries concerned. Similarly, there is no principle of law which enables one to decide whether a rule of law or a legal institution which has proved its value in a national community should be introduced by analogy into international law. The sole valid criterion is whether the present stage of political development of the international community is such as to justify the introduction of the rule or institution in question. In modern international relations, the machinery of judicial settlement has been developed far in advance of the political order in which alone it can effectively operate. Further progress towards the extension of the judicial settlement of international disputes can be made, not by perfecting an already too perfect machinery, but by developing political co-operation. The fact that the members of the British Commonwealth of Nations have hitherto steadfastly refused to set up any kind of permanent and obligatory procedure for the judicial settlement of disputes between one another should serve as a warning to those who are disposed to attach undue importance to the perfection of judicial machinery in international relations. It is a curious paradox that, by signing the Optional Clause of the Statute of the Permanent Court and by excluding from its operation inter-Commonwealth disputes, Great Britain and Dominions are bound in this respect towards many foreign countries by an obligation more far-reaching than they have assumed among themselves.

Projects of ‘all-in arbitration’

Many thinkers of the period between the two wars went, however, far beyond mere plans for the modest and gradual extension of the scope of judicial procedure in international relations. It became a widely cherished ambition to provide, by a stroke of the pen, for the compulsory settlement of all international disputes by arbitration. Schemes for obligatory arbitration were mooted on many occasions prior to 1914, but failed to win acceptance. The Covenant of the League of Nations, while providing for the establishment of the Permanent Court and encouraging the submission of suitable disputes to arbitration or judicial settlement, gave little encouragement to the advocates of obligatory arbitration. In all disputes, it left the choice of the procedure to the discretion of the states concerned; and the political procedure of ‘enquiry by the Council’ always remained open. It was precisely this political aspect of the Covenant which became a target for the attacks of the utopian school. A widespread feeling grew up that the way to establish an international ‘rule of law’ and avoid future wars was for states to submit all international disputes of every kind to an international arbitral tribunal having power to decide them at its discretion on grounds either of strict law or of equity and common sense. Such was the vague conception summed up in the popular catchword of ‘all-in arbitration’. This demand for ‘all-in arbitration’ was supposed to have been met by the Geneva Protocol and by the General Act. It was widely believed that, had the British Government not rejected the Protocol, or had the General Act been accepted without reservations by the principal Powers, a satisfactory procedure would have been in existence for the compulsory arbitration of all international disputes and an important cause of war removed.

But here we come upon an extraordinary confusion, or series of confusions, of thought which, throughout this period, enveloped and obscured the problem of the peaceful settlement of international disputes. When the League Covenant, by an amendment inserted after the establishment of the Permanent Court of International Justice, set ‘judicial settlement’ side by side with ‘arbitration’, ‘arbitration’ meant the verdict of a judge or a tribunal appointed ad hoc, and ‘judicial settlement’ the verdict of a regularly constituted court; and there is no reason to suppose that any other distinction was intended between them. But the misguided attempt to discover an objective distinction between justiciable and non-justiciable disputes led to an equally fallacious distinction between ‘judicial settlement’, meaning the settlement of ‘justiciable’ disputes in accordance with the letter of the law, and ‘arbitration’, meaning the settlement of ‘non-justiciable’ disputes, which were not covered by the letter of the law, on grounds of equity. This conception left its traces on the Geneva Protocol. According to the Assembly report on that instrument, ‘the arbitrators need not necessarily be jurists’, and if they obtain an advisory opinion on any point of law from the Permanent Court, that opinion is ‘not legally binding on them’.10 But the distinction between ‘judicial settlement’ and ‘arbitration’ was first fully developed in the General Act. Under this instrument, disputes ‘with regard to which the parties are in conflict as to their respective rights’ were to be referred to the Permanent Court for ‘judicial settlement’. All other international disputes were to be referred for ‘arbitration’ to an arbitral tribunal. In the absence of any agreed stipulation to the contrary, the tribunal, in pronouncing its judgement was to apply the same rules of law as were applied by the Permanent Court. But ‘in so far as there exists no such rule applicable to the dispute, the tribunal shall decide ex aequo et bono’. This reference to rules of law seems incomprehensible. If the dispute turned on legal rights, it would be submitted not to the arbitral tribunal, but to the Permanent Court. If it did not turn on legal rights, the dispute could not be solved by the application of legal rules. The conception that there is a class of international disputes which arise, so to speak, in vacuo, and are not affected by any existing legal rights or by any rule of international law, is a pure myth.

A more serious confusion is, however, in store. There is a perfectly valid distinction, familiar both in national and in international affairs, between ‘legal’ disputes, arising out of claims which purport to be based on existing legal rights, and ‘political’ disputes arising out of claims to alter existing legal rights. The difference turns, however, not on the nature of the dispute, but on the question whether the complainant seeks his remedy through legal or through political procedure. In the state, claims of the former kind are dealt with by the courts, claims of the latter kind by political action. The individual who fails to get his grievance remedied by a court may seek a remedy for the same grievance through legislation. Internationally, the distinction is less clear cut. No international court is recognized as competent to settle all ‘legal’ disputes, and there is no recognized machinery to settle all ‘political’ disputes. In these circumstances, states making claims against other states are not obliged to make it clear, and do not always make it clear, whether the claim is based on legal rights or is tantamount to a demand to alter those rights. But the distinction, though sometimes obscured in practice, is real enough. Both nationally and internationally, ‘political’ disputes are, generally speaking, more serious and more dangerous than ‘legal’ disputes. Revolutions and wars are less likely to arise from disputes about existing legal rights than from the desire to change those rights. The wise politician, and the wise student of politics, will devote a great deal of attention to political disputes.

When, therefore, it was officially claimed that the Geneva Protocol constituted ‘a system for the pacific settlement of all disputes which might ever arise’,11 or that the General Act provided ‘a comprehensive method of settling all international disputes of whatever character’,12 the conclusion might reasonably have been drawn, and was in fact drawn by many people, that provision had been made for the settlement by arbitration of political disputes, i.e. of disputes arising from claims to modify existing legal rights. Closer inspection did not, however, justify this conclusion. In an inconspicuous passage of the Assembly report on the Protocol, it was explained that the procedure did not apply to ‘disputes which aim at revising treaties and international acts in force or which seek to jeopardize the existing territorial integrity of signatory states’. In fact, added the rapporteur, ‘the impossibility of applying compulsory arbitration to such cases was so obvious that it was quite superfluous to make them the subject of a special provision’.13 The General Act is less ingenuous. It purports to enforce compulsory arbitration for disputes which are not disputes about the ‘respective rights’ of the parties. It purports to authorize the arbitral tribunal to decide such disputes ex aequo et bono. But the authorization applies only ‘in so far as there exists no [legal] rule applicable to the dispute’; and this qualification has the same effect as the reservation in the report on the Geneva Protocol. The essence of a political dispute is the demand that the relevant legal rule, though admittedly applicable, shall not be applied. When a dispute arises through the claim of a state that its existing frontiers, or existing treaty restrictions on its sovereignty, or existing obligations under a financial agreement, are intolerable, it is useless to refer it to an arbitral tribunal whose first duty is to apply the legal ‘rule applicable to the dispute’. The legal right exists and is uncontested. The dispute arises from a demand to change it. Political disputes cannot be settled within the framework of the law by tribunals applying rules of law. The Geneva Protocol and General Act, though purporting to provide for the peaceful settlement of all international disputes, in fact left the most important and dangerous category of international disputes untouched.

No scheme of ‘all-in arbitration’ more inclusive than the make-believe of the Geneva Protocol and the General Act was officially propounded or considered. Some governments were prepared to accept arbitration for such disputes as did not endanger the existing political order – a limitation hardly less restrictive than the vital interests, independence and national honour of the older arbitration treaties. But no government was willing to entrust to an international court the power to modify its legal rights. Some theorists, however, were more ready than practical statesmen to brush this difficulty aside, and were quite prepared to entrust to a so-called arbitral tribunal the task not only of applying existing rights, but of creating new ones. A British organization called the New Commonwealth Society evolved an elaborate scheme for an arbitral tribunal which would ‘determine, on the basis of equity and good conscience, political disputes, including those which have to do with the revision of treaties’, thus establishing ‘an indirect method of legislation in the affairs of nations’ by an equity tribunal.14 Such a scheme would appear to be the necessary corollary of Professor Lauterpacht’s belief that international ‘conflicts of interests are due … to the imperfections of international legal organisation’.15 International conflicts of interests will in future be resolved by a tribunal which will become the supreme organ of world government, exercising not merely the judicial function of interpreting the rights of states, but the legislative function of changing them. Thus will be realized another distinguished international lawyer’s dream of ‘an international legal community whose centre of gravity is in the administration of international justice’.16

These theories have one important merit. They recognize the fallacy, implicit in the Geneva Protocol and the General Act, that an international legal order based on the recognition, interpretation and enforcement of existing rights is an adequate provision for the peaceful settlement of international disputes. But in avoiding this fallacy, they fall into a still graver one. Perceiving that provision must be made for the modification of existing rights, they force this essentially political function into a legal mould and entrust its exercise to a tribunal. Unwilling to recognize the political basis of every legal system, they dissolve politics into law. In this quasi-judicial twilight, the judge becomes the legislator, political issues are settled by an impartial tribunal on grounds of equity and common sense, and the distinction between law and politics disappears.

The extreme difficulty of the international problem is no doubt responsible for the prescription of so heroic a remedy. But the fact that the problem is difficult scarcely justifies us in propounding a solution which nobody regards as either feasible or desirable in our far more highly organized national communities. The obligatory arbitration of international disputes of all kinds is, according to Professor Lauterpacht, ‘a sine qua non of the normal machinery for the preservation of peace’.17 Yet obligatory arbitration of claims not based on legal right is rarely enforced in civilized states, and least of all in those which enjoy the longest record of domestic peace. It does not occur to us to attribute ‘conflicts of interests’ in our domestic politics to the imperfections of our legal organization, or to submit to a national arbitral tribunal, for impartial decision on grounds of equity and common sense, disputes about the necessity of conscription, the abolition of the means test, the legal status of trade unions, or the nationalization of mines. The difficulty is not that we could not find a group of impartial persons deeply imbued with the principles of equity and common sense, but that impartiality, equity and common sense are not the primary, or at any rate not the sole, qualities which we require in a decision of such issues. These are political issues, and are settled by procedure which allows for the intrusion of power, whether in the form of a majority vote, as in democracies, or of the will of a dictator or a party, as in authoritarian states. Neither in democracies nor in authoritarian states are such issues decided by an ‘impartial’ tribunal.

The inapplicability of judicial procedure to ‘political’ disputes

Why then is it necessary, not only in theory, for the sake of clear thinking, but also in practice, for the sake of good government, to preserve this distinction between the legal and political, between issues which we are willing to have settled by judicial procedure on grounds of existing legal rights, and issues which can only be settled by political procedure because they turn on a demand for the modification of existing legal rights?

The first answer is that judicial procedure differs fundamentally from political procedure in excluding the factor of power. When a dispute is submitted to a court, the presupposition is that any difference in power between the parties is irrelevant. The law recognizes no inequality other than inequality of legal right. In politics, the converse presupposition holds. Here power is an essential factor in every dispute. The settlement of a conflict of interest between British agriculturalists and British industrialists will depend, in part at any rate, on their respective voting strength and the respective ‘pulls’ which they can exercise on the government. The settlement of a conflict of interest between the United States and Nicaragua will depend, in greater part (for the ratio of power to other factors is higher in international than in national politics), on the relative strength of the two countries. Conflicts of interest can be dealt with only by an organ which takes the power factor into account. Nothing is gained, and the proper function of law is debased and discredited, if this political function is entrusted to a tribunal whose constitution and procedure are deliberately assimilated to those of a court of law. As Mr Bernard Shaw has remarked, the functions of judge and legislator are ‘mutually exclusive’: the former must ignore every interest, the latter take every interest into account.18

The second answer is equally fundamental. We have seen that even the strictly judicial procedure of a court sometimes entails political pre-suppositions, if only because the application of the law to the particular case is always liable to involve an element of judicial discretion, and this discretion, if it is not to be purely capricious, must draw its inspiration from those presuppositions. Where a tribunal is called upon to decide not on issues of legal right, but on claims to set aside legal rights in favour of equity or common sense, the necessity of clearly defined political presuppositions becomes all the more obvious. In such cases, judicial discretion instead of being limited to points left ambiguous by the law, has infinite scope; and the decisions of the tribunal, if they are not to be mere expressions of individual opinion, must be based on well-established assumptions shared by the community as a whole or by those who speak in its name. The existence of such assumptions in national communities sometimes makes possible the use of arbitration even in political issues; and the same possibility is not entirely excluded in the international sphere. But generally speaking, it is a fundamental obstacle to international arbitration ex aequo et bono that common assumptions of a far-reaching kind scarcely exist in the international community. To submit to an international tribunal, for decision on grounds not of law, but of equity and common sense, disputes concerning British interests in Egypt or the interests of the United States in the canal zone of Panama, or the future of Danzig, or the frontiers of Bulgaria, would have been impracticable, not only because the settlement of these problems involves issues of power, but also because there is no political agreement even of the vaguest kind as to what equity and common sense mean in relation to such questions. On the rare occasions on which international tribunals have been empowered by the parties to decide issues between them on grounds other than those of strict law, the tribunals have shown the greatest reluctance to avail themselves of the discretion accorded to them; not, as Professor Lauterpacht supposes, because ‘law is more just than loose conceptions of justice and equity’,19 but because no responsible tribunal cares to commit itself on any important issue to an authoritative pronouncement as to what is ‘equitable’ or ‘just’ in international relations. An international tribunal, once it has left the comparatively solid ground of international law and legal rights, can find no foothold in any agreed conception of equity or common sense or the good of the community. It remains, in Professor Zimmern’s words, ‘an array of wigs and gowns vociferating in emptiness’.20

The crux, however, remains. Political issues, both nationally and internationally, are far more menacing than issues of legal right. The periodical, or rather the constant, revision of existing rights is one of the prime necessities of organized society; and to bring about revision in the international society by means other than war is the most vital problem of contemporary international politics. The first step has been to extricate ourselves from the blind alley of arbitration and judicial procedure, where no solution of this problem is to be found. Having taken this step, we are free to approach it by other, and perhaps more promising, avenues.

Notes

1.

|    |

Permanent Court of International Justice, Series 2, No. 5, p. 27.

2.

|    |

Disputes ‘as to the interpretation of a treaty’ are the first category of dispute recognized by the Covenant as ‘generally suitable’ for judicial settlement. It is noteworthy that the framers of the Covenant, who drew up this article, nevertheless rejected a proposal to insert in the Covenant a provision that disputes as to its own interpretation should be submitted to the Permanent Court (Miller, The Drafting of the Covenant, ii. pp. 349, 516). Behaviour in concrete cases is sometimes more significant than the enunciation in vacuo of abstract rules.

3.

|    |

Lauterpacht, The Function of Law in the International Community, p. 369 and passim. It is a pity that Professor Lauterpacht, having brilliantly conducted his analysis up to the point where the unwillingness of states is recognized as the limiting factor in the justiciability of international disputes, should have been content to leave it there, treating this ‘unwillingness’, in true utopian fashion, as perverse and undeserving of the attention of an international lawyer.

4.

|    |

The British Government, in its memorandum of 1928 on arbitration (League of Nations: Official Journal, pp. 694–704), criticized general arbitration treaties on the ground that, in the case of every country, ‘obligations which it may be willing to accept towards one state it may not be willing to accept towards another’.

5.

|    |

Quoted in Taracouzio, The Soviet Union and International Law, p. 296.

6.

|    |

Proceedings of the Hague Peace Conference (Engl. transl.: Carnegie Endowment), Conference of 1907, ii. p. 316.

7.

|    |

On the latter occasion, Professor Gilbert Murray, representing South Africa on the Assembly of the League of Nations, lamented that a judicial question (i.e. compensation for Italy) had been brought before a political organ and decided on political grounds (League of Nations: Fourth Assembly, pp. 139 sqq.) – an excellent example of the fallacy, so trenchantly exposed by Professor Lauterpacht, that certain issues are ipso facto judicial.

8.

|    |

Roscoe Pound, Law and Morals (2nd ed.), p. 62.

9.

|    |

Professor Laski remarked many years ago that ‘the foreigner in the United States cannot but observe with the deepest wonder how eagerly possible nominations for a vacant position on the Supreme Court are canvassed’ (Introduction to English translation of Duguit, Law in the Modern State, p. xxiii). The wonder has grown less deep since the political character of the Court has been better understood.

10.

|    |

League of Nations: Fifth Assembly, First Committee, p. 486.

11.

|    |

League of Nations: Fifth Assembly, p. 497.

12.

|    |

Memorandum on the General Act, Cmd 3803, p. 4.

13.

|    |

League of Nations: Fifth Assembly, p. 194.

14.

|    |

Lord Davies, Force, pp. 73, 81.

15.

|    |

Lauterpacht, The Function of Law in the International Community, p. 250.

16.

|    |

Kelsen, The Legal Process and International Order, p. 30.

17.

|    |

Lauterpacht, The Function of Law in the International Community, p. 438.

18.

|    |

G. B. Shaw, John Bull’s Other Island, Preface.

19.

|    |

Lauterpacht, The Function of Law in the International Community, p. 252.

20.

|    |

Zimmern, The League of Nations and the Rule of Law, p. 125. The words are applied to Taft’s international arbitral court. They could be applied, still more appositely, to the equity tribunal advocated by the New Commonwealth Society.

CHAPTER THIRTEEN

Peaceful Change

Recognition of the need for political change has been a commonplace of thinkers of every period and every shade of opinion. ‘A state without the means of some change’, said Burke in a famous phrase, ‘is without the means of its own conservation.’1 In 1853, Marx wrote trenchantly on the Eastern question:

Impotence…expresses itself in a single proposition: the maintenance of the status quo. This general conviction that a state of things resulting from hazard and circumstances must be obstinately maintained is a proof of bankruptcy, a confession by the leading Powers of their complete incapacity to further the cause of progress and civilization.2

And Professor Gilbert Murray has put the same point in a different form:

War does not always arise from mere wickedness or folly. It sometimes arises from mere growth and movement. Humanity will not stand still.3

It appears to follow from this view that the attempt to make a moral distinction between wars of ‘aggression’ and wars of ‘defence’ is misguided. If a change is necessary and desirable, the use or threatened use of force to maintain the status quo may be morally more culpable than the use or threatened use of force to alter it. Few people now believe that the action of the American colonists who attacked the status quo by force in 1776, or of the Irish who attacked the status quo by force between 1916 and 1920, was necessarily less moral than that of the British who defended it by force. The moral criterion must be not the ‘aggressive’ or ‘defensive’ character of the war, but the nature of the change which is being sought and resisted. ‘Without rebellion, mankind would stagnate and injustice would be irremediable.’4 Few serious thinkers maintain that it is always and unconditionally wrong to start a revolution; and it is equally difficult to believe that it is always and unconditionally wrong to start a war. Everyone will, however, agree that war and revolution are undesirable in themselves. The problem of ‘peaceful change’ is, in national politics, how to effect necessary and desirable changes without revolution and, in international politics, how to effect such changes without war.

Every effective demand for change, like every other effective political force, is compounded of power and morality; and the object of peaceful change can be expressed in terms neither of pure power nor of pure morality. It is rather unprofitable, except as an academic exercise, to enquire whether the purpose of any change should be to establish ‘justice’, by remedying ‘just’ grievances, or to maintain ‘peace’, by giving satisfaction to those forces which would otherwise be strong enough to make revolution or war. But it is dangerous to suppose that the two purposes are identical, and that no sacrifice of one or the other is required. Every solution of the problem of political change, whether national or international, must be based on a compromise between morality and power.

The role of power in political change

The necessary role of power in political change will be ignored only by the most superficial observers. Few ‘revisionist’ campaigns in history have been more firmly based on moral considerations than that of the Dreyfusards in France. Yet the protest against the condemnation of Dreyfus would never have been effective if it had not been taken up by powerful political organizations and used by them as a weapon against political opponents. The grievances of Albania and Nicaragua, whatever their moral basis, will never be effective unless they are endorsed, for interested reasons, by some Great Power or Powers. It is fair to attribute the growth of social legislation in the last hundred years to a growing realization of the just grievances of the working class. Yet these results would never have been achieved without the constant use, or threatened use, of force in the form of strikes and revolutions. ‘It is true’, remarks Mr John Strachey, ‘that governments always tell us that they will never yield to force. All history tells us, however, that they never yield to anything else.’5 ‘Peaceful secession!’ exclaimed Daniel Webster in 1849. ‘Sir, your eyes and mine are never destined to see that miracle.’6 ‘The winning back of the lost territories’, wrote Hitler in a famous passage of Mein Kampf, ‘is not achieved through solemn invocations of the Lord God or through pious hopes in a League of Nations, but through armed force.’7 Hitler might even have appealed to the respectable authority of Gladstone who, in the days when liberalism was still a political force, observed that ‘if no considerations in a political crisis had been addressed to the people of this country except to remember to hate violence and love order and exercise patience, the liberties of this country would never have been obtained’.8 It has been said that no ruling class ever abdicates of its own accord. Article 19 of the Covenant of the League of Nations remains a lonely monument to the pathetic fallacy that international grievances will be recognized as just and voluntarily remedied on the strength of ‘advice’ unanimously tendered by a body representative of world public opinion.

While, however, the fundamental problem of political change – the compromise between power and morality – is identical in national and in international politics, the question of procedure is complicated by the unorganized character of the international community. Analogies drawn from procedures of change in the national sphere can only be applied with caution to the international field. We have seen that judicial procedures cannot be invoked, either nationally or internationally, for the solution of ultimate political problems. But the analogy of legislation seems at first sight more hopeful. The legislative process, unlike the judicial process, recognizes the role of power which is inherent in all political change (for the legislative authority is the supreme power of the state imposing its will on the whole community); and legislation, which a German writer has called ‘legal revolution’,9 is the most obvious and regular way of bringing about political change within the state. ‘What is peaceful change as an effective institution of international law or of international society?’ asks Professor Lauterpacht, and answers: ‘It is the acceptance by states of a legal duty to acquiesce in changes in the law decreed by a competent international organ.’10

It has already been noted that international law rests upon custom, and that there is at the present time no such thing as international legislation or an international legislature. The terms of Article 19 of the Covenant show how remote the principal states were in 1919 from ‘acceptance of a legal duty to acquiesce in changes in the law decreed by a competent international organ’. Nor can this well be otherwise. Reflexion will show that the legislative process, like the judicial process, presupposes the existence of a political order. It is only by that combination of consent and coercion which underlies every political society that we can arrive at the establishment of a supreme organ, whether parliament or council of state or individual autocrat, whose fiat creates law binding on all members of the community. These conditions are not fulfilled in the international community. The Assembly of the League of Nations, whose decisions required unanimity, was a conference empowered to conclude international agreements, not a legislature which passed international legislation; for, as Mr Eden bluntly observed at one of its sessions, ‘it would plainly be impracticable…to give the Assembly power to impose changes against the wish of the parties concerned’.11 The difficulty lies not in the lack of machinery for international legislation, but in the absence of an international political order sufficiently well integrated to make possible the establishment of a legislative authority whose decrees will be recognized as binding on states without their specific assent. If we accept Professor Lauterpacht’s identification of peaceful change with international legislation, we can only conclude that, in his words, ‘an international system of peaceful change…runs the risk of being unreal unless it forms part and parcel of a comprehensive political organization of mankind’.12 The condition of international legislation is the world super-state.

Need we, however, reconcile ourselves to the discouraging conclusion that any international system of peaceful change must await the coming of the super-state? The analogy of legislation may turn out to be not merely discouraging, but misleading. The present almost universal belief in the beneficence of legislation as a reforming instrument within the state is in the main a growth of the past fifty years. Down to the end of the nineteenth century, many intelligent people continued to regard the state as a necessary evil and legislation as a regrettable device not to be resorted to except in case of proven necessity.13 Within the national community, the distinction familiar to nineteenth-century thought between ‘society’ and ‘state’ has lost much of its significance through the development of the social functions of the modern state. But in the international sphere, we are in the presence of a ‘society’ which has no corresponding ‘state’; and we may therefore find some help in the conception, which would hardly have seemed paradoxical to any age but our own, of changes peacefully effected in the social structure without legislation or any other overt form of state intervention. Even to-day, it is easy to exaggerate the role of legislation; and it may still be true to say (as it would certainly have been true a hundred years ago) that the most important changes in the structure of society and in the balance of forces within it are effected without legislative action. It may be unnecessarily pessimistic to rush into the conclusion that the absence of an international legislature rules out any international procedure of peaceful change.

If, therefore, we are looking for the nearest analogy in the national community to the turbulent relations which render the problem of change acute in the international society, we may find it in the relations of those group-entities within the state whose conflicts have not been in the past, and still in large measure are not, settled by any legislative process. Of these group-entities, by far the most important, and by far the most instructive for our purpose, are those representing capital and labour respectively. Here we have the same recurrent conflict between ‘haves’ and ‘have-nots’, between ‘satisfied’ and ‘dissatisfied’; the same reluctance, on the part of one or both sides, to accept the principle of ‘all-in arbitration’ for the settlement of their disputes; the same recognition of the inapplicability or inadequacy of the legislative process; the same appeals to ‘law and order’ by the satisfied group; and the same use, or threatened use, of violence by the dissatisfied in order to assert their claims. It is sometimes said that there can be no international procedure of peaceful change so long as states insist on being judges in their own cause. Here is a class of disputes in which both parties commonly insist on being judges in their own cause, and in which some progress at least has been made towards an orderly procedure of peaceful change.

Force has always been a crucial factor in relations between capital and labour. In the beginnings of the industrial revolution, every attempt at organized self-help on the part of the workers was rigorously repressed. This unqualified repression ended in Great Britain with the repeal of the Combination Acts in 1825, and continued in Russia as late as 1905. Between those two dates, the workers of every important industrial country secured recognition of their right to use the weapon of the organized strike. The strike not only proved itself an effective instrument for extracting concessions from employer to workers, but became a recognized symbol of the major weapon of force – revolution.14 In recent times, the element of force has been once more eliminated from relations between employer and workers by the authoritarian governments of Soviet Russia,15 Italy and Germany, through legislation prohibiting strikes and an executive strong and ruthless enough to enforce the prohibition. Democratic countries have from time to time prohibited strikes, though such prohibitions have nearly always been resisted by the workers, and have rarely proved enforceable over an extended period.16 Theoretically, force might in the same way be eliminated from the settlement of international disputes by a powerful and authoritarian super-state. But this result, whether desirable or not, lies outside the scope of practical consideration; and we shall therefore find a better analogy to the international position if we consider those countries and those periods in which relations between capital and labour have not been dominated by the overwhelming power of the state. In the latter part of the nineteenth century and the first part of the twentieth the ‘have-nots’ of most countries steadily improved their position through a series of strikes and negotiations, and the ‘haves’, whether through a sense of justice, or through fear of revolution in the event of refusal, yielded ground rather than put the issue to the test of force. This process eventually produced on both sides a willingness to submit disputes to various forms of conciliation and arbitration, and ended by creating something like a regular system of ‘peaceful change’. In many countries such a system has been in operation for many years with remarkable success, though the ultimate right to resort to the weapon of the strike is not abandoned. If we could apply this analogy to international relations, we might hope that, once the dissatisfied Powers had realized the possibility of remedying grievances by peaceful negotiations (preceded no doubt in the first instance by threats of force), some regular procedure of ‘peaceful change’ might gradually be established and win the confidence of the dissatisfied; and that, once such a system had been recognized, conciliation would come to be regarded as a matter of course, and the threat of force, while never formally abandoned, recede further and further into the background. Whether the analogy is in fact valid, or whether this hope is purely utopian, is a question which can hardly be settled except by the test of experience. But one may record with some confidence the view that this is the only line of advance which affords any prospect at all of the establishment of any international procedure, however imperfect, of peaceful change.

The implication of this procedure must, however, be clearly recognized. Few issues of social or political change of sufficient magnitude to involve the risk of revolution or war can be settled without detriment, or apparent detriment, to the interests of one of the parties. That the party at whose expense the change was to be effected would acquiesce in it without the existence of means of pressure to compel him to do so was one of the strange illusions of the ill-fated Article 19 of the Covenant; and this illusion may be discarded. Such self-abnegation could indeed hardly have been expected. The statesman, the trade union leader or the company director is a trustee for those whose interests he represents; and in order to justify extensive concessions at their expense, he must generally be in a position to plead that he has yielded to force majeure. When the change is effected by legislation, the compulsion is that of the state. But where the change is effected by the bargaining procedure, the force majeure can only be that of the stronger party. The employer who concedes the strikers’ demands pleads inability to resist. The trade union leader who calls off an unsuccessful strike pleads that the union was too weak to continue. ‘Yielding to threats of force’, which is sometimes used as a term of reproach, is therefore a normal part of the process.

The parallel should not be pressed too far. The role of force, even in the most advanced democratic states, is indeed more constant and more conspicuous than most sentimental democrats care to admit. In so orderly a country as Great Britain, during the present century, force has been used or threatened for securing political ends by Ulstermen, Irish nationalists, female suffragists, communists, fascists and organized workers. But within the state there are checks on the too hasty resort to force. In the first place, the legislative process exists, and provides an alternative method of change; faith in the ballot-box has deterred the workers of many countries from revolutionary policies. Secondly, the state makes some show (often an imperfect one) of holding the balance impartially between the parties on the issue in dispute. Thanks to these checks, a certain moral discredit attaches in democratic countries, in the minds of all classes, to the open use or threat of force until other means have been tried of bringing about a change.

In international politics neither of these checks exists. The use or threatened use of force is therefore a normal and recognized method of bringing about important political change, and is regarded as morally discreditable mainly by those ‘conservative’ countries whose interests would suffer from change. The largest operation of ‘peaceful change’ in the nineteenth century was that performed by the Congress of Berlin, which revised the treaty imposed by Russia on Turkey at San Stefano. But this revision took place only under the tacit threat of a declaration of war against Russia by Great Britain and Austria-Hungary.17 The Lausanne Treaty of 1923 was a revision, extorted by the use and threatened use of force, of the treaty signed with Turkey at Sévres in 1920. It was denounced by Lloyd George as ‘an abject, cowardly and infamous surrender’; and this opinion was widely held at the time.18 The revision of Czecho-Slovakia’s frontiers effected by the Munich Agreement of September 1938 was also the product of a threat of force; and here we have the explicit testimony of M. Benes that no alternative method was available. For five years earlier he had publicly stated ‘that no country could be forced by anyone to revise its frontiers, and that anyone who attempted it in the case of Czecho-Slovakia would have to bring an army along’.19 Another curious example may be added. When Poland annexed Vilna in 1920, Lithuania closed the frontier and severed all communications with Poland. It is doubtful whether this isolation conferred any advantage on Lithuania. But no Lithuanian statesman could have justified the reopening of the frontier and the consequent loss of face to his country if he had not been in a position to plead force majeure. In March 1938, Poland mobilized an army and presented an ultimatum to Lithuania. The frontier was at once reopened; and normal relations were established. An operation of peaceful change, generally recognized as salutary, could not be effected save under a threat of war. Normally, the threat of war, tacit or overt, seems a necessary condition of important political changes in the international sphere.20

This principle has not only been demonstrated in practice on many occasions, but received a large measure of theoretical recognition from the framers and interpreters of the Covenant of the League of Nations. The machinery of the League was brought into action by the danger of war. Article 11 related to ‘any war or threat of war’ and to ‘any circumstance…which threatens to disturb international peace’; and Article 19 purported to deal with treaties which have become inapplicable’ (a phrase which has never been satisfactorily explained) and with ‘international conditions whose continuance might endanger the peace of the world’. Moreover, the most effective article of the Covenant for promoting peaceful change, and the only one which was ever invoked for the purpose,21 was not Article 19 but Article 15, under which recommendations could be made without the concurrence of the parties concerned, and might, in the event of war, be supported by sanctions. But the only condition which could bring this article into operation was a ‘dispute likely to lead to a rupture’. The grievances of which the Covenant took cognizance were, broadly speaking, the grievances of states strong enough to create a danger of war. In 1932, when Finland brought before the Council a claim against Great Britain arising out of the commandeering of Finnish ships in the first world war, the British Government argued inter alia that there was no case to go to the Council, since the dispute was not in the least ‘likely to lead to a rupture’. In the same year, the British Government brought before the Council under Article 15 a dispute with Iran arising out of the affairs of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. The essential difference was that Great Britain was strong enough to create the danger of a rupture, and Finland was not.22 When Article 19 was invoked for the first time by Bolivia in 1921, it was cogently argued that, since the conditions of which Bolivia complained had existed for a long period without endangering peace, there was no case for bringing them before the League. In other words, it would have been necessary, in order to set the procedure of peaceful change in motion, that Bolivia should be strong enough to threaten war against Chile. The doctrine of the Covenant thus confirmed the lesson of experience that peaceful change could not be effected on any important scale in international politics in the absence of a threat, or potential threat, of war.

We may sum up the conclusions so far reached. The judicial process is unfitted to solve the problem of peaceful change in national, and a fortiori in international, politics; for, treating the parties to a dispute as equal, it fails to recognize the element of power which is a necessary factor in every demand for change. The legislative process, though recognizing the role of power and well adapted to meet many demands for change in national politics, is inapplicable to international demands for change, since it pre-supposes the existence of a legislative authority whose decrees are binding on all members of the community without their specific assent. There remains the bargaining process, which is applied to some demands for change within the state and is alone applicable to demands for international change, since states (like trade unions or employers’ federations) insist on the ultimate right to accept or reject any solution offered. But whereas under the legislative process change is enforced by the power of the state, change under the bargaining process can be enforced only by the power of the complainant. Power, used, threatened or silently held in reserve, is an essential factor in international change; and change will, generally speaking, be effected only in the interests of those by whom, or on whose behalf, power can be invoked. ‘Yielding to threats of force’ is a normal part of the process of peaceful change.

This is one side of the picture; and since it is the side which is ignored in most modern writing about international politics, it has been deliberately emphasized here. Nor should we underrate the value of peaceful change even considered solely from this point of view. If relations between employers and workers are such that the former cannot resist, or the latter cannot sustain, a demand for an increase in wages and a reduction in hours, it is preferable (quite apart from any question of the justice or injustice of the demand) that it should be conceded or rejected as the result of peaceful negotiations rather than as the result of a long and embittered strike which half ruins both employers and workers. If the relations of power between the leading European countries in 1877 made it inevitable that Bulgaria should be deprived of much of the territory allocated to her by the Treaty of San Stefano, then it was preferable that this result should be brought about by discussions round a table in Berlin rather than by a war between Great Britain and Austria-Hungary on the one side and Russia on the other. If we consider peaceful change merely as a more or less mechanical device, replacing the alternative device of war, for readjusting the distribution of territory and of other desirable things to changes in the equilibrium of political forces, it performs a function whose utility it would be hypocritical to deny. Many changes made in national communities, whether by legislation or otherwise, and recognized as salutary, have no other basis than this.

The role of morality in political change

Nevertheless, it is clear that there is another aspect of peaceful change which occupies men’s thoughts, and that it is no more possible to discuss peaceful change than to discuss any other kind of political procedure in terms of power alone. When a contested demand for change is made, the question which immediately exercises the minds of most people is whether it is just. It is true that our view of its justice is likely to be coloured, and may be wholly determined, by our own interest. It is true that, if our interest is not strongly engaged, we shall be tempted to discover reasons for regarding as just a solution which seems inevitable, or which could only be avoided by a great effort on our part. It is also true that, here as in every other political issue, power plays a part in determining our moral outlook, so that we shall be disposed, other things being equal, to regard a solution desired by the strong or the many as juster than a solution desired by the weak or the few. But when all these allowances have been made, the view taken of the morality of the transaction – a view not wholly determined by considerations of power – will influence the attitude of the mass of people affected by it. ‘If orderly government is to command general assent,’ writes Mr Bertrand Russell, ‘some way must be found of persuading a majority of mankind to agree upon some doctrine other than that of Thrasymachus’;23 and if an orderly procedure of peaceful change is ever to be established in international relations, some way must be found of basing its operation not on power alone, but on that uneasy compromise between power and morality which is the foundation of all political life. The establishment of a procedure of peaceful negotiation in disputes between capital and labour presupposes, not merely an acute perception on both sides of the strength and weakness of their respective positions at any given time, but also a certain measure of common feeling as to what is just and reasonable in their mutual relations, a spirit of give and take and even of potential self-sacrifice, so that a basis, however imperfect, exists for discussing demands on grounds of justice recognized by both. It is the embryonic character of this common feeling between nations, not the lack of a world legislature, and not the insistence of states on being judges in their own cause, which is the real obstacle in the way of an international procedure of peaceful change.

How far is this common feeling operative in relation to demands for international change? Clearly in some degree. Two concrete cases of demands for change may be selected for analysis, one from the quasi-international, the other from the international sphere.

In the nineteenth century, the demand for home rule for Ireland found among a large number of people in Great Britain a support based not on considerations of power, but on common recognition as a canon of international morality of the right of ‘oppressed nationalities’ to self-determination and on a certain readiness to sacrifice self-interest to it. The stock of common feeling between Great Britain and Ireland was considerably greater than that commonly existing between two foreign countries. Nevertheless, the demand for change did not become effective until, owing to the diversion of British military strength elsewhere, force could be placed behind it. If the compromise eventually arrived at in 1921 could have been achieved in 1916, it would have been a true example of peaceful change achieved, like most international examples of peaceful change, under threat of war. But even in 1921, the settlement could not have been reached, and above all could not have been lasting, solely on a basis of power. The Anglo-Irish Treaty was a flagrant case of ‘yielding to threats of force’: it was concluded with the authors of a successful rebellion. But it had its necessary moral foundation in the acceptance of a common standard of what was just and reasonable in mutual relations between the two countries, and in the readiness of both (and particularly of the stronger) to make sacrifices in the interest of conciliation; and this made a striking success of an agreement about which the gloomiest prognostications were current at the time of its conclusion.

The second example is the failure to achieve a peaceful settlement with Germany in the period between the two world wars. The mass of political opinion in Great Britain and Germany (and in most other countries) agreed for many years that a criterion of justice and injustice could properly be applied to the Versailles Treaty; and there was a surprisingly considerable, though far from complete, consensus of opinion about the parts of it which were just and unjust respectively. Unfortunately, Germany was almost wholly deficient for fifteen years after 1918 in that power which is, as we have seen, a necessary motive force in political change; and this deficiency prevented effect being given, except on a minor scale, to the widespread consensus of opinion that parts of the Versailles Treaty ought to be modified. By the time Germany regained her power, she had adopted a completely cynical attitude about the role of morality in international politics. Even though she continued to base her claims on grounds of justice, she expressed them more and more clearly in terms of naked force; and this reacted on the opinion of the status quo countries, which became more and more inclined to forget earlier admissions of the injustices of the Versailles Treaty and to consider the issue as exclusively one of power.* The easy acquiescence of the status quo Powers in such actions as the denunciation of the military clauses, the reoccupation of the Rhineland or the annexation of Austria was due, not wholly to the fact that it was the line of least resistance, but in part also to a consensus of opinion that these changes were in themselves reasonable and just.24 Yet they were greeted in each case by official censures and remonstrances which inevitably created the impression that the remonstrating Powers acquiesced merely because they were unable or unwilling to make the effort to resist. Successive removals of long recognized injustices of the Versailles Treaty became a cause not of reconciliation, but of further estrangement, between Germany and the Versailles Powers, and destroyed instead of increasing the limited stock of common feeling which had formerly existed.

It is beyond the scope of the present book to discuss the present or future foreign policy of Great Britain or of any other state. But the defence of the status quo is not a policy which can be lastingly successful. It will end in war as surely as rigid conservatism will end in revolution. ‘Resistance to aggression’, however necessary as a momentary device of national policy, is no solution; for readiness to fight to prevent change is just as unmoral as readiness to fight to enforce it. To establish methods of peaceful change is therefore the fundamental problem of international morality and of international politics. We can discard as purely utopian and muddle-headed plans for a procedure of peaceful change dictated by a world legislature or a world court. We can describe as utopian in the right sense (i.e. performing the proper function of a utopia in proclaiming an ideal to be aimed at, though not wholly attainable) the desire to eliminate the element of power and to base the bargaining process of peaceful change on a common feeling of what is just and reasonable. But we shall also keep in mind the realist view of peaceful change as an adjustment to the changed relations of power; and since the party which is able to bring most power to bear normally emerges successful from operations of peaceful change, we shall do our best to make ourselves as powerful as we can. In practice, we know that peaceful change can only be achieved through a compromise between the utopian conception of a common feeling of right and the realist conception of a mechanical adjustment to a changed equilibrium of forces. That is why a successful foreign policy must oscillate between the apparently opposite poles of force and appeasement.

Notes

*

|    |

This reaction was, of course, intensified by Nazi Germany’s domestic policy.

1.

|    |

Burke, Reflections on the Revolution in France (Everyman ed.), p. 19.

2.

|    |

Marx and Engels, Works (Russian ed.), ix, p. 372.

3.

|    |

Gilbert Murray, The League of Nations and the Democratic Idea, p. 16.

4.

|    |

B. Russell, Power, p. 263.

5.

|    |

J. Strachey, The Menace of Fascism, p. 228.

6.

|    |

Quoted in J. Truslow Adams, The Epic of America, p. 239.

7.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 708.

8.

|    |

Quoted in E. Pethick-Lawrence, My Part in a Changing World, p. 269.

9.

|    |

Berber, Sicherheit und Gerechtigkeit, p. 9.

10.

|    |

Peaceful Change, ed. C. A. W. Manning, p. 141.

11.

|    |

League of Nations: Seventeenth Assembly, p. 46.

12.

|    |

Peaceful Change, ed. C. A. W. Manning, p. 164.

13.

|    |

Professor Lauterpacht’s remark that ‘the circle of interests directly regulated by law expands with the growth of civilization’ (The Function of Law in the International Community, p. 392) is a truism to-day, but would have seemed a paradox to many nineteenth-century thinkers.

14.

|    |

This is the significance of the ‘one-day strike’, which was popular in certain countries and which, though useless in itself, was designed to demonstrate that the workers were strong enough to break the power of the state. The success or failure of the one-day strike was thus a test of power, and its result enabled both sides to draw the appropriate conclusion without resorting to extreme measures.

15.

|    |

The position is not substantially affected by the fact that in Soviet Russia the employer is normally a state trust or institution.

16.

|    |

In Great Britain, strikes in munitions factories were prohibited during the first world war by the Munitions of War Acts. But though strikes occurred, the law was rarely if ever enforced, and it came to an end with the War. Under the Trade Disputes Act of 1927, political strikes were declared illegal, but no such case appears to have arisen since the act was passed. The situation in other countries is summarized in a pamphlet published by the American League for Industrial Democracy (Shall Strikes be Outlawed? by Joel Seidman), which concludes that ‘labour feels that its right to strike is its surest guarantee of fair treatment’ and that ‘along the path of voluntary collective bargaining lies the greatest hope of satisfactory industrial relations’.

17.

|    |

A writer who has surveyed the history of peaceful change down to 1914 records the conclusion that ‘it is always wisest to face Europe with a fait accompli’ (Cruttwell, History of Peaceful Change, p. 3).

18.

|    |

D. Lloyd George, The Truth About the Peace Treaties, ii. p. 1351.

19.

|    |

The Times, 26 April 1933, quoted by Professor Manning in Politica, December 1938, p. 363.

20.

|    |

Those who assert that change effected under a threat of armed force is not ‘peaceful change’ are, of course, at liberty to define their terms how they please. But it should be noted that a definition thus restricted would equally exclude changes effected by a legislative or judicial process, if these required enforcement. If Czecho-Slovak territory had been transferred to Germany in September 1938 by a decision of the League Assembly or of an equity tribunal, enforced by mobilizing the armies of the League or an international police force, the change would not for that reason have had any better title to the epithet ‘peaceful’. Armed force would have been used in precisely the same way.

21.

|    |

The Special Assembly, dealing with the Manchurian dispute under Article 15 of the Covenant, endorsed the recommendations of the Lytton Commission for substantial modifications of the status quo in Manchuria. It need hardly be added that Japanese military action was the force which prompted these recommendations, which proved, however, insufficient to satisfy Japan.

22.

|    |

In the Finnish question, M. Madariaga expressed the view that ‘it was extremely dangerous for the Council, the Assembly, and the League of Nations to establish the doctrine that irascible parties would be listened to, and calm parties would not, because in the latter case there would be no question of a rupture’ (League of Nations: Official Journal, November 1934, p. 1458). The defect of the Finnish case was, however, not so much that Finland was calm as that she was weak.

23.

|    |

B. Russell, Power, p. 100.

24.

|    |

In Great Britain, a perusal of the British press for 7 and 8 March 1936 will show how widely the reoccupation of the Rhineland was not merely tolerated, but welcomed. Subsequently, the tone of the press became less favourable, being manifestly influenced by the more critical official attitude.